music
music
In the Central Research Institute,
In the Central Research Institute,
the lecture will begin on August 4th.
the lecture will begin on August 4th.
Please welcome Wang Huijun, the Deputy Director of the Dean of the Department of Education.
Please welcome Wang Huijun, the Deputy Director of the Dean of the Department of Education.
applause
applause
Dear friends and colleagues,
Dear friends and colleagues,
I AM Wang Hui Jun.
I am Wang Huijun.
Thank you very much for coming to this feast of knowledge
非常感謝各位來參加這一場的知識饗宴
The feast of knowledge in the Central Plains has a history of many years
中原的知識饗宴已經有蠻多年的歷史
There have always been very, very good speakers to give us incisive speeches in simple terms
一直都有非常非常好的講員來替我們做深入淺出的精闢演講
Here I want to remind me that after the speech is over, the next time will be announced
這邊要提醒我說演講結束要預告下一次
I think it's better to announce it first, or I will forget later
我想還是先預告一下 不然等一下我會忘掉
Therefore, the feast of knowledge in September is organized by Associate Researcher Lei Xianglin
所以9月份的知識饗宴是由雷祥林副研究員
Our Institute of Modern History of the Central Plains
我們中原的近代史的研究所
He's going to give a lecture that has something to do with life.
他要來主講跟生命也有點關係
Due to the meaning of Du Congming
由於杜聰明的意思
The Mystery of Du Congming's Chinese Medicine Research
杜聰明的漢醫藥研究之謎
Traditional Medical Sciences and Modernity in East Asia
傳統醫療科學與東亞的現代性
So it must have been a pretty good speech.
所以一定也是一個蠻精采的演講
So please come to participate in September
所以請各位9月的時候要來參加
I am very happy to invite you to the feast of knowledge in the Central Plains today
今天非常高興請到中原的知識饗宴
Institute of Molecular Biology
分子生物研究所
We all have a branch office
我們都有叫分生所
early annullosis
分生所早期
Why is it called split life?
為什麼叫分生呢
Because wife and husband are often
因為太太跟先生常常是
live in a different place
在不一樣的地方生活
So either the wife is in the US
所以要嘛就是太太在美國
Or the wife is in Taiwan
要嘛就是太太在台灣
So this branch office was established around 1988
所以這個分生所在1988年左右成立的
So it has a history of more than 20 years and almost 30 years
所以也有二十幾年快三十年的歷史
Our Sun Yihan designated researcher
我們孫宜翰特定研究員
Is that time to come into the branch office
是那時候進來分生所
In the early days, I also participated in the establishment of some branch offices
早期的時候我也參與了一些分生所的建立
Dr. Sun Yihan
孫宜翰博士
What he writes here is very interesting
他這邊寫的很有趣
He said he graduated from Hsinchu Middle School
他說他是新竹中學畢業的
In 1974, he gave up the medical department of National Taiwan University
1974年放棄台大的醫科
Then the first choice was to enter the Department of Botany, National Taiwan University
然後第一志願進入台大植物系
I don't know why you do this kind of thing
我不知道你為什麼要做這種事情
but anyway
不過anyway
But I also gave up on this
不過我也放棄了這個
I don't have a medical degree from National Taiwan University
我沒有台大醫科的程度
I said that at that time, I heard that the score seemed to be able to enter Kaohsiung Medical University.
我說那時候分數聽說好像可以進高雄醫學院
But I didn't read one either
但是我也沒有唸一個
I went to study chemistry
我去唸化學學系了
Anyway, after he graduates
Anyway,那他畢業了以後
After graduation in Taiwan
在台灣畢業以後
to America's top universities
就到美國的第一流的大學
Caltech to do research in biology
加州理工學院去做生物方面的研究
biological research over there
那邊生物研究
Caltech I also took
加州理工學院我也帶過
that very small school
那非常小的一個學校
But all professors are top professors
但是所有的教授都是頂尖的教授
Who is Mr. Anyway?
那Anyway老師是誰?
Leah Wood
Leah Wood
Leah Wood is also a very legendary figure
Leah Wood也是一個非常傳奇性的人物
Maybe wait a minute, Mr. Sun can introduce us
也許等一下這個孫老師可以跟我們介紹一下
Like the sequencing of this modern DNA
像這個近代的這個DNA的定序
Also developed by Leah Wood
也是Leah Wood那邊開發出來
commercialize it
讓他可以商品化
So Mr. Sun at Caltech
所以孫老師在加州理工學院
After a very solid training
做了非常扎實的訓練以後
Go to 125th University as a postdoctoral fellow
到一二五大學去做博士後
It's been a while
那過了不久啊
He returned to Taiwan in 1988
他就一九八八年就回到台灣
Join us as an associate researcher
到我們分身所當副研究員
that he made very contact
那他做得非常接觸
but you can tell
但是你可以看出來
He did not become a professor in three years
他並沒有三年就生教授
why do you know
為什麼你知道嗎
Because Mr. Sun is very rigorous in running the academy
因為孫老師做學院非常的嚴謹
he must do
他一定要是做
Either do the best or don't do it
要嘛去做最好的不然就不要做
So he worked hard
所以他就很細心努力的
to make these studies very touching
去把這些研究做得非常接觸
That's a coincidence too
那這個也很巧
After our recent Dean Liao Junzi came back
我們最近廖君子院長回來以後
He just emphasized that we should plant but not quantity
他就是強調說我們要種植不種量
In the past, everyone was aiming at a lot of papers
以往的話大家都衝著一大堆論文
But that plant is not so good
但是那個植不是那麼好
What Taiwan lacks now is high-quality research
我們台灣現在缺的是高品質的這些研究
Whether it is innovation
不管是創新也好
or to have a lot of this
或者是要有很多的這個
How do you say this in basic research?
怎麼講的在基礎研究的話要有這種
Guide to the updated field
引導到更新的領域
So Mr. Sun is the cultural hygiene in this area
所以孫老師是這方面的文化衛生
he did very well
他做得非常好
However, in addition to doing a good job in this research, he
不過他除了這個研究做得好以外
Twenty or twenty years ago, he was known as our so-called Special Review Researcher
那二二快十年前他就被稱為我們所謂的特評研究員
That's a very rare thing
那這是非常難得的事情
Teacher Sun has been using this fruit fly
那孫老師一直在利用這個果蠅
He just told me the reason why his eyes are red
他剛才跟我講這個為什麼眼睛紅紅的道理
wait a minute and he'll explain it to us
等一下他會跟我們說明
Drosophila was used very early to create what we call animal models
果蠅是很早的時候被用來創造一種我們叫動物模式的動物
Actually, you already talked about using animal mode once
其實你已經講過一次用動物模式
A few years ago, it seemed that there was a self-made response
幾年前好像也講過一次自製相應
Today we are going to talk about the fruit fly
今天是特別來講這個果蠅相關的
I just saw that fruit fly and I figured it has six legs
那果蠅我剛才看我算算有六隻腳
I asked him why
我就問他說他為什麼
what are those eight legs
那八隻腳的是什麼
He said spiders have eight legs
他說蜘蛛是八隻腳
Fruit flies are something different
果蠅是不一樣的東西
fruit flies are insects
果蠅是昆蟲
what is a spider
蜘蛛是什麼
anyway so do I really understand
anyway 所以我真的是不是很懂
But the fruit fly because of its disease model
不過果蠅因為它這個疾病模式
or wait for the creation
或者是等等的創造
has been around for many years
已經有很多年的歷史
it has something to say
它這邊有講說
has several nobel prizes
有好幾個諾貝爾講
from the study of fruit flies
是因為研究果蠅而來
especially genetically
尤其在遺傳方面
it requires understanding of development
它要了解發育學
words of development biology
development biology的話
Drosophila is indispensable
果蠅是不可或缺的
There are quite a lot of people who make fruit flies in our country
我們國內做果蠅的人也相當的多
There are also very touching
也有做得非常接觸
There is a group of people in our Central Plains Institute
我們中原院有一群人
Animals that specialize in different disease models
專門利用不一樣的疾病模式的動物
for neural research
來做神經相關的研究
This Teacher Sun is a teacher in this field
這個孫老師是這方面的教教者
He leads a group in our Central Plains Academy
他領導我們中原院有一群
specialized in neuroscience research
專門在做神經科學研究的
Our English name is NPASS
我們英文名字叫NPASS
Neuroscience Program at the Academia Cineca
Neuroscience Program in Academia Cineca
This laboratory with thirty or forty researchers is participating in this program
這個現在有三四十個研究人員的實驗室參與這個program
Our Teacher Sun has led this group of people from the very beginning
我們孫老師從一開始就是領導這一群人
So he plays a very important role in neuroscience in Taiwan
所以他在神經科學在台灣是扮演很重要的角色
A pusher in many fields
很多領域的推手
So he has won many awards
所以他也得過了很多的獎
I have seen this young researcher's book award
我這邊有看到這個年輕研究人員的著作獎
This is very rare in Academia Sinica
這個在中研院是非常難得
NSC End-of-Research Award
國科會的研究結束獎
Ministry of Education Academic Awards
教育部的學術獎
This is already top in our Academia Sinica
這個在我們中研院已經是頂尖了
Because we can't take the award as the professor's award here
因為我們這邊不能拿獎做教授的獎
Hou Jindui, etc.
侯金堆等等
so many honors
所以非常的多的榮譽
But what I admire most about him is
但是他最讓我敬佩的是
His spirit of public service is very important
他的這種公共服務的精神是非常重要
very very rare
非常非常的難得
He was the convener of the Biology Department of our National Science Council
他當過我們這個國科會的生物學們的召集人
Then in our TCM Hospital Academic Consulting Association
然後在我們中醫院學術諮詢總會
Also served as our Deputy Executive Secretary for Life Sciences
也當過我們生命科學方面的副執行祕書
A while ago, he also became the vice-chairman of the National Science Council.
前一陣子國科會他也當到了副主委
that is very difficult
那這是非常不容易的事情
That's in the vice-chairman's tenure
那在副主委的任內
He also promotes these recombinations of these biological
他也推動這些生物學們的這些重新組合
So contribute a lot
所以貢獻得非常大
Recently, of course, the Ministry of Science and Technology has a neuroscience project
最近當然這個科技部有一個神經科學專案
he is our convener
他是我們召集人
So today he is going to tell us some research about the fruit camp
所以今天他要來跟我們講一些關於果營的研究
In addition to their very touch
除了自己做的很接觸
He will introduce other relevant
他會介紹一下其他相關的
So his topic "Little Fruit Builds a Great Communist Party"
所以他的題目小小果營立大共
The contribution of this fruit camp to human development and disease research
那這個果營對於人類發育跟疾病研究的貢獻
what the hell
到底是怎樣
so welcome to take care of the teacher
所以歡迎我們順理一下老師
Soft Block Mineral Gaster
Soft Block Mineral Gaster
Mineral Gaster Gaster
Mineral Gaster Gaster
So we divide it into AQ
所以我們把它分一張為AQ
that is also called wind
那也有叫做風
The fruit flies like this are what you usually think of
那這樣的果蠅跟大家平常想到
the kind that endangers business
危害營業的那種
Chinese style
中方國式
Then the inner class feels different
然後內類的感覺是不一樣的
Fruit flies coexist with humans
果蠅跟人類共存
as long as someone is in one place
只要有人在一個地方
or in spark water
或是在火花水的話
can see
就都看得到
eat rotten fruit
吃腐爛的水果
so it doesn't harm us humans
所以它不會危害我們人類
Doesn't it carry anything on it that affects what
它身上不攜帶任何會影響什麼
or some of our accelerated
或者我們加速的一些併據
Then it can also take anything
然後它也能帶任何東西
Will affect the fruits and watercolors you think it doesn't hurt us
會影響你以為它不傷害我們的水果和水彩
it eats rotten fruit
它會吃腐爛掉的水果
has rotted
已經腐爛了
But such a
但這樣的一個果然
it is at...
它在...
Its life is very fierce
它的一生非常的狠戰
from a city from
從一個城從
hold very poor mating
持著很窮的交配
It should have a setting on it
它身上應該有一個設定
This platform is below our normal temperature at 25 degrees
這個培台在25度時有我們的常溫之下
Just give it a piece a day
要一天就給它一塊就好了
Then it will go through 30% to 60% of the period
然後它要經過三、六成時期
Then it will separate its exoskeleton
然後它要把它的外骨隔了
Do not return it and then make an impression
不退掉 然後再做印象
then just give it life
然後就給它的生命
Life in this fruit camp is very interesting
這個果營的生活是非常的有趣
Here we emphasize that its development
這裡我們強調說它的這個發育
I will tell the temperature
我都會講那個溫度
Because insects it is not like we are cross-temperature
因為昆蟲它是不像我們是橫溫
so the temperature inside its body
所以它的身體內部的溫度
changes with the outside temperature
是隨著外界的溫度改變
so the temperature is higher
所以溫度高一點
Its whole development process will be faster
它的整個發育過程就會比較快
The lower the temperature, the slower its growth
那溫度低一點它的發育就慢
So we can use temperature to adjust
所以我們可以用溫度來調整
Then its life is probably normal
那它的生活大概平常
We can be between 16 degrees and 30 degrees
我們可以在16度到30度之間
can raise it
都可以養它
So we're talking about 25 degrees here
所以我們這裡講25度
On that day, the embryo will be skinned.
那一天這個胚胎就膚化出來
Then one day after another
然後一零又蟲有一天
Twenty Another Bug Day
二零又蟲一天
Three Zeros and Worms have three days
三零又蟲有三天
The only thing it has to do at this point
在這個時候它唯一要做的事情
Just eat in the food
就是鑽在食物裡面吃
So its behavior is backlight
所以它的行為是背光
then to the ground
然後向地
It burrows into that fruit and eats it
它就鑽在那個水果裡面吃
When it arrives, its body grows
到了然後它的身體就長大
In the late period of the three zeros and worms
到了三零又蟲的晚期
it has a huge transformation
它就有一個很巨大的轉變
Its behavior changed, it became like a light background
它行為改了 它變成像光背地
it crawls out of the food
它就從食物裡面爬出來
then find a clean place
然後再找一個乾淨的地方
its shell hardens
它的外殼就變硬
Then it starts to form a yong
然後它就開始結一個雍
that's in this yong
那在這個雍裡面
Its entire body was almost completely knocked out and redone
它的整個身體幾乎完全打掉重做
Many of these heavy cells are dying
很多的這個又重的細胞要死掉
Then part of the cells start to rebuild a body
然後部分的細胞開始重新做一個身體
so we call it a complete metamorphosis
所以我們叫做完全變態
Because the individual that grew up
因為長出來的這個個體
It's totally different from heavy
跟又重是完全不一樣的
That's the same thing as a caterpillar turning into a butterfly
這就是毛毛蟲變蝴蝶同樣的事情
So what about this life history?
所以這一個生活史呢
it basically develops twice
它基本上發育兩次
first time its in a short time
第一次它在很短時間
In a day it makes a heavy body
一天之內它就做出一個又重的身體
It can move, eat, and perform various behaviors
那可以動 可以吃 有各種的行為
Then when it's time to kill and redo
然後到了擁的時候打掉重做
long a completely different
長一個完全不同的
it's late
那到了擁的晚期
Chest is about five days
胸大概是五天
Then he will open the chest shell
那他就要把這個胸殼打開
he has a sac on his head
他的頭上有一個囊
He'll beat his bodily fluids into the sac
他會把他的體液打到囊裡面去
There is a bag on the head
頭上就鼓起一個包
Then let him break through the cover on the chest
然後就把這個胸上面的蓋子給他突破
then he crawled out
然後他就爬出來
crawled out with his wings tucked together
爬出來他的翅膀是縮在一起
Then he slowly spread his wings
然後他就慢慢翅膀睜開
then become a mature individual
那就變成一個成熟的個體
What about the adult worm that hatched like this?
那這樣孵出來的這種成蟲呢
It takes about 12 hours to believe that they are mature enough to mate
大概12個小時就信成熟就可以交配
and then the next generation
然後就產生下一代
So very interesting life history of a
所以非常有趣的一個生活史
Why do we use fruit flies as materials
我們為什麼會要用果蠅作為材料
Then we are now doing research on many organisms
那我們現在對很多的生物的研究
A very important center is the gene
很重要的一個中心就是基因
The fruit flies are being studied because
那果蠅會作為研究是因為
He can easily find genetic mutations
他很容易找遺傳的突變
his genes can
他的基因可以
we can do screening
我們可以做篩選
Well, any living thing can mutate
那其實任何生物都會發生突變
However, the probability of mutation is usually not high
可是突變的機率通常不高
Not high, about one thousandth of a thousandth
不高大概是千分之一萬分之一
Let's say one in ten thousand
那我們就說萬分之一
You need 10,000 fruit flies
你就要有一萬隻果蠅
you can pick a mutant
你可以挑到一隻突變種
is what you want
是你想要的
If it is a mouse
假如是老鼠
You need 10,000 mice
你就要有一萬隻老鼠
Then this is huge and expensive
那這個就很龐大很貴
If you want to use elephants
假如是要用大象
Those 10,000 elephants are unlikely to be able to conduct experiments
那一萬隻大象就不太能夠做實驗
So Drosophila is a multicellular organism
所以果蠅是多細胞生物裡面
easier to feed
比較容易飼養
Its life cycle is short
那它的生命週期短
Can give birth to many at a time
一次可以生很多隻
then we can control its mating
那我們可以控制它的交配
easy to feed
很容易飼養
can reproduce in large numbers
可以大量繁殖
that its body is small
那它的個體很小
We live in a small bottle
我們養在一個小瓶子裡面
You can raise two hundred
就可以養個兩百隻
So it takes up very little space
那所以占用的空間很小
that's basically cheap
那基本上就很便宜
And fruit flies I'll talk about later
然後果蠅我等一下要講
it's been over a hundred months
它已經經過一百多個月
years of research so there are very, very many
多年的研究 所以有非常非常多的
resources for this research we have established a very good
這個研究的資源 我們建立了很好的
Purebred strains, so-called purebred strains are
純種的品系 那所謂純種品系就是
Between one of its fruit camps and another fruit camp
它的一支果營跟另外一支果營之間的
This change is very small, it is very different from people
這個變化非常的小 這跟人就很不一樣
Each person, this inheritance between two people
每一個人 兩個人之間的這個遺傳
Variations are very, very many
變異非常非常的多
So this makes it an experiment
所以 這個就使得做起實驗來
It's a little simpler and then we also
它比較單純一點 然後我們也
After many years of research across the field
經過非常多年 整個領域的研究
built many, many tools that allow us to manipulate
建立了很多很多的工具 讓我們可以做操控
So it has a lot of the convenience of these experiments above
所以它有很多這些實驗上面的方便
Then with these conditions, we can go to filter
那有了這些條件以後 我們就可以去篩選
The picture changes, let's talk about it later
圖變 這個等一下再講
Then Tubian will find the gene of Tubian
那圖變就找到圖變的基因
Find this gene, it causes the result of this map change
找到這個基因 那它造成這樣的圖變的結果
We know that this gene is related to this function
我們就知道說這個基因跟這個功能有關係
So build it like this
所以就建立了這樣子
know that if the gene is mutated
知道這個基因假如發生突變
it causes some kind of disease
它會造成某種病
then we can ask
那我們就可以問說
Then why does this disease occur?
那這個病為什麼會產生
Except for this gene
除了這個基因以外
What other genes are also involved
還有哪些其他的基因也參與
So in this way we will treat the disease
所以這樣我們就對這個病的
Mechanism of healing
治病的機制
will have a more in-depth understanding
會比較有一個深入的了解
Once we know the mechanism
一旦我們知道這個機制
why do you get sick
為什麼你會得病
Which genes are changed
哪些基因發生了變化
We can design some strategies to treat
我們就可以設計一些策略去治療
you target a gene
你針對某個基因
Design certain drugs against a certain protein
針對某個蛋白設計某些藥物
or drug screening
或者做藥物的篩選
So this is what fruit flies can use in
所以這個就是果蠅可以用在
The human disease we're going to talk about today
我們今天要講的這個人類疾病
Use above
上面之用
then why fruit flies
那為什麼用果蠅
Just said it's cheap
剛剛已經講它很便宜
and it's fast
而且做起事情來很快
because you make a fruit fly
因為你做一個果蠅
you're only two weeks old
你才一代兩個禮拜
12 days
12天
We can easily do several generations of genetic experiments
我們可以很容易的做好幾代的遺傳實驗
As long as you use a mouse, it will take a long time
只要用老鼠那就要好長時間
As long as you use elephants, it will be even worse.
只要是用大象那就更不得了
So just do a few things quickly
所以就做幾事情來快
And after more than a hundred years of accumulation
而且經過了一百多年的累積
have a lot of knowledge
有非常非常多的知識
Presumably there isn't a single other multicellular organism
大概現在沒有任何一個其他多細胞的生物
we know so much
我們了解的這麼多
Accumulated a lot of research resources
累積了很多的研究資源
Another very important thing is
還有一個很重要的就是
The group of people who studied the fruit camp from the very beginning
從一開始研究果營的這一群人
It is the tradition established by the first big brother
就是最早的大佬他建立的傳統
makes everyone think
就使得大家認為
Resource information for all research
所有研究的資源資訊
Should be to share is to share
都應該是要Share是要共享
that this is very important
那這個是非常重要
This is actually why I chose to do fruit camp back then
這事實上是為什麼我當年選擇去做果營
Because at that time I wanted to say that I would go back to Taiwan in the future
因為那時候想說我將來要回台灣
that was nearly 30 years ago
那個將近30年前
we are very worried
我們非常擔心
I am worried that if I return to Taiwan, I will be cut off from the world
我擔心說回到台灣會跟世界隔絕
So as a fruit fly, I feel like I can get all this information
所以做果蠅我就覺得這些資訊我都可以拿得到
I can get all the mutants from others
人家的突變種我都可以要得到
Until now, the tradition of this community has been maintained like this.
一直到現在這個社群的傳統還是這樣子維持下來
The third important thing is that fruit flies are actually very similar to people
第三個重要的是果蠅其實跟人很像
About 75% of these genes cause disease in humans
大概有75%在人裡面會致病的這些基因
We can find it all in fruit flies
在果蠅裡面我們都可以找得到
So fruit flies can be used to study human disease
所以可以用果蠅來研究人類的疾病
We'll talk more about this later
這個我們等一下還要再講很多
One more thing I think is also very important is
再來一個我覺得也很重要就是
There are also single-celled organisms that are more convenient for us to study
也有單細胞的生物我們更方便去研究
Siomyces bacterium
肖母菌細菌
It's faster and cheaper for all the things just said
所有剛才講的東西它都更快更便宜
But it's a little boring
可是就有一點乏味
it is not a multicellular organism
它不是多細胞生物
Look at a Xiaomai fungus, it is round like that
你看一個肖母菌它就是那樣圓圓的
it looks boring
看起來就無趣了
The various conditions it can have
那它能夠有的這些各種各樣的狀況
Also different from us
也跟我們人比較不一樣
But what about fruit flies?
可是果蠅呢
Even its nervous system is similar to ours
就連它的神經系統都跟我們人很像
it has various behaviors
它有各式各樣的行為
are very close to people
都跟人非常的接近
so we can use it to study things that humans are interested in
所以我們可以用它來研究人類有興趣的事情
it's simple enough and complex enough
那它夠簡單又夠複雜
So the complexity is just right
所以複雜程度剛好
The study of the fruit fly began in 1910
那果蠅的研究從1910開始
I just said fruit flies are everywhere
剛我說果蠅是到處都有
So in early labs it was very easy for you to have fruit flies coming in from outside
所以早期的實驗室很容易你就有外面的果蠅飛進來
Then just raise it and play it
然後就養一養的玩一玩
Until 1910 this Thomas Hunt Morgan
直到1910這個Thomas Hunt Morgan
He is at Columbia University
他在Columbia大學
Then he started to find a fruit fly
那他開始發現了一隻果蠅
Fruit flies normally have red eyes
果蠅正常的是紅眼睛
The one he found was white eyes
他找到的這一隻是白眼睛
And this white-eyed fruit fly he mated it
而且這一隻白眼睛的果蠅他把它交配交配
I found out that white eyes are hereditary
就發現這個白眼是可以遺傳的
And this white eye always follows the gender
而且這個白眼是永遠跟著性別走
it only appears in males
它只在雄性才會出現
So we know it's a recessive mutation
所以就知道這是一個隱性的突變
Then it's sex-linked
然後它是性連遺傳
It follows the sex chromosome X chromosome
它跟著性染色體 X染色體走
So from here it published a paper a paper
所以從這裡它發表了一篇paper 一篇論文
that proves the gene
那證明了基因
This was originally an abstract concept
這個原本是一個很抽象的觀念
gene it proves it's located on a chromosome
基因它證明它位在染色體上
Chromosomes are things we can see under a microscope
染色體是一個我們顯微鏡底下看得到的東西
So let's make this gene an entity
所以就讓這個基因變成了一個實體
Then you can do research and experiment
然後是可以做研究做實驗
So because of this study
所以因為這個研究呢
it won the nobel prize in 1933
它在1933年得了諾貝爾獎
That early Drosophila research
那早期的果蠅的研究
Found that Drosophila has this giant chromosome
發現果蠅有這種巨染色體
It's just a chromosome its DNA replicates replicates replicates
它就是一個染色體它的DNA複製複製複製
But it doesn't separate, unlike our normal chromosomes that will separate after duplication
可是它不分開 不像我們一般這種染色體複製以後就會分開
it's all connected
它就通通連在一起
So it will replicate ten times. Two to the tenth power is a thousand times.
所以它會複製十次 二的十次方就是一千倍
A thousand chromosomes, a thousand pieces of DNA glued together
一千條染色體 一千條DNA黏在一起
so it becomes big
所以就變成很大
under the microscope when very large
很大的時候在顯微鏡底下
At that time, only optical microscopes
那個年代只有光學顯微鏡
Under the microscope, you can see such a dark and light-colored
在顯微鏡底下就可以看得到這樣的一個有這種深色淺色的這種
This type of pattern is fixed
這樣的pattern這樣的型態是固定的
Every cell in every fruit fly is the same
每一個果蠅每一個細胞都是一樣
so it can position it
所以它就可以把它定位
Sometimes such chromosomes will appear
有的時候這樣的染色體會出現狀況
There will be a sweep in the middle
中間會有一段掃掉
Because you can see the shape of the chromosome, you will know which section to scan
染色體因為你形狀看得出來你就知道哪一段掃了
what kind of mutation
造成什麼樣的突變
You know that gene is located in this section
你就知道那個基因位在這一段裡面
So utilize a tool like this
所以利用這樣的工具
twenty or thirty years
就有二三十年的時間
just did a lot of work
就做了很多很多的工作
Know the behavior of chromosomes
知道染色體的行為
How chromosomes recombine
染色體怎麼發生重組
How come something missing these
怎麼會產生一些缺失這些
How are the genes passed on?
那基因怎麼傳遞
Then the location of the gene on the chromosome
然後基因在染色體上面的定位
So about thirty years or so
所以大概有三十年左右的時間
just two things
就只有兩樣東西
is extremely important in genetics
是在遺傳學極為重要
one is fruit camp
一個是果營
one is corn
一個是玉米
one animal one plant
一個動物一個植物
That's all because their chromosomes are special
那都是因為他們的染色體很特別
So you can track chromosomal changes
所以可以去追蹤染色體的變化
So this is Morgan
那這個是Morgan在
His Fly Group at Columbia University
Columbia大學他的Fly Group
very shabby one
很破爛的一個
Bananas hanging on a laboratory wall
一個實驗室牆上都掛了香蕉
Then there are glass jars with fruit flies
然後有玻璃瓶的養著果蠅
But such a laboratory
可是這樣一間實驗室
Dominate modern genetics for about 30 years
Dominate現代遺傳學大概30年
Then there's Morgan
那這裡面呢就Morgan
Then Muller et al.
然後Muller等下講到
He also took the Norbell speech
他也拿了Norbell講
Then the other two disciples of Morgan
然後另外兩位Morgan的弟子
Both Britjus and Sturdivus are masters of genetics
Britjus和Sturdivus都是遺傳學大師
about 30 years
也有大概30年的時間
Genetics is fruit fly plus corn
遺傳學就是果蠅再加上玉米
That Morgan's students include this one
那Morgan的學生包括這一位
Herman Muller
Herman Muller
He also made a lot of contributions
那他也做了很多的貢獻
The most important thing is
那最被最重要的一件事情是
He discovered that taking fruit flies and taking them to X-rays
他發現把果蠅拿去照X光
will produce a mutation
就會產生突變
X-rays break chromosomes
X光會把染色體打斷
genetic changes
以後就造成基因的變化
So this one is
所以這個一個是
is to tell us that radiation can damage our DNA
就是告訴我們說輻射線會破壞我們的DNA
will cause mutation
會造成突變
Well, this was way before the atomic age.
那這個還是早在原子能時代之前
But later it affected our consideration of this radiation.
可是後來就影響了我們對這個輻射線的考慮
The other is that you can artificially take X-rays
另外一個是你就可以用人為的方式照X光
Later, I switched to taking some drugs to produce mutations
後來改用吃一些藥物可以產生突變
Mutation can be done for research
產生突變就可以做研究
why is this important
為什麼這很重要
Because Morgan when he found that one mutation
因為Morgan那時候他找到那一個突變
It just fell from the sky
那完全是天上掉下來的
the chances of that are very very low
那機率非常非常低
then you take your luck doing research
那你要做研究就碰運氣
But once you can artificially promote mutations
可是一旦你可以人為去促進突變的發生
You have a much higher chance of getting the mutation
你得到突變的機率就高很多
So it becomes very convenient
所以就變成非常的方便
But the good times don't last long
可是好景不長
it's the same tool
就是同樣的工具
If you ask these questions to a certain level, you will not be able to continue asking them.
你問這些問題 問到一個程度你就問不下去了
all done
該做的都做完了
So to 1940 5060
所以到了1940 5060
Drosophila becomes obsolete
果蠅就變成沒落
has fallen to such an extent that almost no one is doing fruit flies anymore.
沒落到一個程度 幾乎沒有人再去做果蠅
Bacteria and viruses were the most popular at that time
那個時候最熱門的是細菌和病毒
Do these genetic studies faster
做起這些遺傳研究更快
So a lot of people put in
所以非常多人投入
that ushered in a new era
那開創了新的一個時代
Fruit flies are eliminated
果蠅就被淘汰了
It was 1970
那到了1970
Only then did someone apply these new molecular biology techniques
才又有人把這些新的分子生物的技術
brought it back and used it on fruit flies
重新拿回來用在果蠅身上
Because fruit flies have a very good knowledge in the past
因為果蠅過去有非常好的知識
So he introduced this new technology
所以他把這個新的技術引進來
As a result, a lot of previous
結果就把很多之前
It is important to know that there is no way to study these issues
知道重要沒有辦法研究下去的這些問題
Take it back for research
重新拿回來研究
The second golden age of the fruit fly
就中了果蠅的第二個黃金年代
until now
一直到現在
I should have said a moment ago
那我剛剛應該講一個
this chromosome
這個染色體
When I was in college, I told Wang Feichang
我大學的時候我跟王飛長說
I study botany
我念植物系
we'll have genetics
我們就上遺傳課
Geneticists did genetic experiments
遺傳家做了遺傳實驗
raising fruit flies
養果蠅
and look at this giant chromosome under a microscope
然後在顯微鏡底下看這個巨染色體
That fruit fly raised
那果蠅養起來
That food smells bad after fermentation
那個食物發酵以後就很臭
we have to wash the bottles
我們要洗瓶子
Stinks
很臭
I swore I would never touch a fruit fly again.
就發誓以後再也不要碰果蠅
Then look at this microscope
然後看這個顯微鏡
i get dizzy
我會頭暈
because of the quick movement
因為很快的動動
will be dizzy
就會頭暈
I also swore never to touch a microscope again.
也發誓以後再也不要碰顯微鏡
It's too early to say
那話都講得太早
As a result, later
結果後來就
will do it for decades
就要做個幾十年
Ok so I'm back to this fruit fly picture
好那我回到這個果蠅的圖片
here are some
這裡列了一些
these funny pictures
這些很有趣的圖片
This is Wild Type
這個是Wild Type 野生型
that's what we call normal
就是我們講說正常
red eyes with wings
紅眼睛有翅膀
then have six legs
然後有六隻腿
This is the first Baiyan Guoying I found
這個是第一個找到的白眼果影
The pigment in his eyes is gone
他眼睛的色素不見了
Then the same gene can have different forms of pictures
那同一個基因可以有不同形式的圖片
This one is called White Apricot
這一個叫做White Apricot
his eyes are not so red
他的眼睛沒有那麼紅
Pigment becomes lighter
色素變得比較淡
Still a picture of the same gene
還是同一個基因的圖片
This fruit shadow with its wings rolled up is called Curly
這一隻果影他的翅膀捲起來叫做Curly
This one has his body turned into Yellow
這一隻他身體變成Yellow
from black to yellow
從比較黑變成比較黃
It's also a matter of pigment
也是色素的問題
This one will be mentioned later
這一隻等下還會再提到
Called Illus and he has no eyes
叫做Illus 他就沒有眼睛了
He's all right, but his eyes are missing.
他身體一切正常可是眼睛不見了
So earlier studies did a lot of this
所以早期的研究做了很多這種
image above form
形態上面的圖片種
We know that such mutations are related to development
我們知道這樣突變就跟發育有關
What about some other mutations?
那另外有一些突變呢
he died
他就死掉了
Mutation occurs and he dies
發生突變他就死了
What can you do when you die?
那死了你能夠怎麼辦
You told me that this gene is very important
你就告訴你說這個基因很重要
so without him
所以缺他就不行
what else to do
除此之外還能做什麼
Someone used it to study his death
有人就把它拿來研究他死相
when did he die
他死在什麼時候
What happens to your body when you die?
死的時候身體發育到什麼狀況
You know he can develop to this stage
你就知道他可以發育到這個階段
Indicates that the gene is at this stage
表示這個基因在這個階段
before is not important
之前是不重要的
Then at this stage it is important
然後在這個階段是很重要
so he can't go on
所以他走不下去
so you can know a lot
所以也可以知道很多
Then you can also design various
那你還可以去設計各種各樣
Interesting way to screen for mutations
有趣的篩選突變的方法
For example, someone did a screening
譬如說有人做了一個篩選
Because he really can fly
他就因為果然會飛
He put Guoruo in a cage
他把果然關在一個籠子裡
Same network power
同網通電
then go knock
然後就去敲
Those who can fly will fly up and hit the Internet
那會飛的果然就飛起來碰到網上
electrocuted
就電死了
the flightless fruit camp
那個不會飛的果營
just survive
就活下來
that won't fly
那不會飛
you can imagine it has several possibilities
你就可以想像它有好幾種可能
one is that it may not have wings
一個是它也許沒翅膀
so you can study wing development
所以你可以研究翅膀的發育
one is that it has wings
一個是它有翅膀
but it can't fly
可是它不會飛
won't fly it may be because
不會飛它可能是因為
Problems with the muscles that control flight
控制飛的肌肉出的問題
Or a problem with the nerves that control the flight
或者控制飛的神經出的問題
Or a problem with the control of the brain
或者說大腦的控制出的問題
So it can be divided into many more
所以又可以再分很多
So the same filter
所以同樣這種篩選
you can find a variety of these mutations
你就可以找到各種各樣不同的這些突變
So how to design this screening mutation
那怎麼去設計這種篩選突變
it's a very interesting place
就是非常有意思的地方
Then as the years passed, we continued to
那隨著年代我們就陸陸續續
There are several important techniques
有好幾種重要的技術
Then we can put the genes back in the fruit camp.
那我們可以把基因放回到果營裡面去
we can do whatever we want
我們可以隨心
want to control this gene
所欲的控制這個基因
let it show where
讓它在什麼地方表現
what time to show
什麼時間去表現
We can be inside a fruit eagle individual
我們可以在一個果鷹的個體裡面
Let some of its cells be damaged
讓它某一部分細胞是壞掉的
some cells are good
某一部分細胞是好的
So making this genetic fit
所以製造這種遺傳的堪合體
Now we have new technology
現在我們有新的技術
let us do whatever we want
讓我們可以隨心所欲的
you don't rely on mutations
你不是靠突變
just happen naturally
只是天然發生
But I just want to change this one gene
而是我就想要改變這一個基因
I change it like an engineer
我就像工程師一樣去改它
So for Guoying
所以對果鷹來講
Now we can pretty much do whatever we want
現在我們幾乎隨心所欲的
in any particular cell
在任何特定的細胞
specific time
特定的時間
we can have a way to change
我們可以有辦法去改變
A certain gene its expression or its function
某一個基因它的表現或者它的功能
The precision of such manipulation
那這樣的操控的精細度
Can also be done in other creatures
在別的生物也可以做
But the precision is far less than
可是精細度遠遠比不上
here
這裡講的
We can do the same in mice
我們在老鼠裡面也可以做
Of course it is much more expensive and much slower
當然就貴很多慢很多
But the precision of manipulation
可是操控的精細度
far inferior to fruit eagle
遠遠比不上果鷹
Fruit eagle has many benefits
果鷹還有很多好處
Its genome was sequenced in 2000
它的基因體在2000年就已經定序了
this ordered paper
這一篇定序的論文
There are so many authors working together
就有這麼多的作者大家一起合作
Not just the genetic sequencing of a fruit eagle
還不只是一支果鷹的基因定序
Also did 12 different sequences
還做了12種不同的定序
the total can be compared
總和總就可以比較
If we take two total DNA sequences and compare
假如我們拿兩個總的DNA序列去比較
what they have in common
他們共通的部分
may be more important in evolution
就可能在演化上面比較重要
so will be kept
所以會被保留下來
they will change
他們會有變化的
Probably something less important
大概就是比較不重要的東西
So this allows us to quickly
所以這樣就讓我們可以很快的
to focus on the important parts
去聚焦在重要的那些部分
I'll talk about it again
再來我就講一下
this development
這個發育
Drosophila begins with a fertilized egg
果蠅一開始一個受精卵
just a cell
就是一顆細胞
This cell divides many times
這顆細胞要經過很多次的分裂
after the split
分裂之後呢
It's going to look like this when it's an embryo
它會在胚胎的時候就變成一個這樣子
You can see that this already has some body segments
你可以看到這已經有一些體節
it is divided into many body segments
它分割成很多的體節
That's a total of fourteen verses
那總共是有十四節
The basic structure of an insect is the head
昆蟲基本上的構造是頭部
boobs then belly
胸部 然後腹部
The three parts of the head, chest and abdomen
頭胸腹三個部分
what about the chest
胸部呢
Always three quarters
一律都是三節
This is SORAC
這個是SORAC
So T1 T2 T3
所以T1 T2 T3
Each of the three sections grows a pair of legs
那三節每一節長一對腿
Then the second section grows a wing
然後第二節會長一個翅膀
In the third section, a small wing will grow
第三節呢會長一個小小的翅膀
called a balance bar
叫做平衡棒
That abdomen has A1 to A8
那腹部有A1到A8
eight knots
八節
That
那
Abdomen no longer have legs
腹部就沒有長腳了
that such a heavy body structure
那這樣的沉重的身體構造
Actually
其實在
Black Fetus, Late and Larval Stages
黑胎、晚期和幼蟲時期
can already see
就已經都看得出來
so it's in a short time
所以它在很短時間之內
somites
就產生這樣的體節
Let me show you one
那給大家看一個
Movie
電影
Um
嗯
I just tried it and it still works
剛才試的是還可以放
ok then
好 那就
No way, I was going to show you this one
沒辦法 本來要給大家看它的這個
early developmental process
早期發育的過程
that same
那同樣的
You can tell it has these segments
你可以知道它是有這些體節
someone made one
就有人做了一個
screening mutations
篩選突變
and it finds this with all sorts of mutations
它就找到有各式各樣突變的這種
This dying embryo
這種會死掉的胚胎
dead in embryo
死在胚胎裡面
like this one
像這一個呢
just compare with normal
就跟正常的去比
it's like the body
它好像身體
this colored piece
這一有彩色的這一塊
all gone
統統都不見了
so is this
那這個也是一樣
All these colored parts are gone
所有這些有彩色的部位都不見了
gone here too
這裡也不見了
So from the analysis of these mutant species
所以從這些突變種的分析
The order in which they discovered
他們發現的發生的先後順序
A very important structure like this comes out
就得出來一個很重要的這樣的架構
That is, the embryo must first determine the head and tail from the early stage
就是胚胎從早期先要決定頭和尾
Then through a series of genes
然後經過一系列基因的作用
Divide this embryo step by step into 14 somites
把這個胚胎逐步分成14個體節
that part is very important
那這一部分非常的重要
But it's complicated
可是講起來很複雜
easy to bring
很簡單帶過
Such research won a Nobel Prize
這樣的研究得了諾貝爾獎
After it is divided into 14 body segments
那分成14個體節以後
grow into a mature individual
長成一個成熟的個體
Each body segment has a different structure
每一個體節長出來的結構都不一樣
I just talked about this T2
剛才我講過這個T2
The second section of the chest will grow wings like this
胸部第二節會長這樣的翅膀
What about the third part of the chest?
那胸部第三節呢
Such a small balance bar
長這樣一個小小的平衡棒
Nothing grows in the first section of the chest
胸部第一節什麼都沒長
have a mutation in a gene
有一個基因的突變
This gene is called UBX
這個基因叫做UBX
Just let this T3
就讓這個T3
The third section grows exactly like the second section
第三節長成了跟第二節完全一樣
So what about a fruit fly?
所以這樣一隻果蠅呢
Now there are two T2
現在有兩個T2
there are two pairs of wings
就有兩對翅膀
that's very interesting
那這個非常的有趣
except this one looks like a monster
除了這個像個怪獸一樣
very interesting
非常有趣
The change creates a difference between the two body segments
改變就造成了兩個體節的差異
However, the two body segments are quite different in shape.
而這兩個體節在形態上差很多
So a genetic shift changes the past
所以一個基因的轉變就改過去了
another one
再來一個
This is Guoying's head and this side is the secondary eye
這個是果鷹的頭這邊是副眼
this is the mouth
這是嘴巴
and here are its tentacles
然後這裡是它的觸角
antennum
antennum
Here's another mutation
這又有一個突變
It makes this tentacles completely into feet
它讓這個觸角完全變成了腳
This is a very complete leg
這是一個很完整的腿
The legs are divided into many knots
腿分了好多節
So this one mutation is called antennanum pedia
所以這一個突變叫做antennum pedia
pedia is feet
pedia就是腳
Same it a gene change
同樣的它一個基因的改變
Make the original two forms above
使得原來兩個形態上面
very different structures
差別很大的結構
One tentacles and one foot transforms
一個觸角和一個腳就發生了轉變
say these two
表示說這兩個
The difference in the two body structures is only in the
這兩個身體結構的差異就只在
a gene
一個基因
So this gene controls
所以這樣的基因就控制了
the development of a part of the body
身體某一部分的發育
The part of the embryo mentioned earlier
那前面講的這個胚胎部分的
these two did it
是這兩位做的
And then the double-breasted fruit camp behind this
然後這個後面這個雙胸果營
This Al-Louis did it
是這一位Al-Louis做的
The three won the Nobel Prize together in 1995
那這三位在1995年共同獲得諾貝爾獎
Then you say OK this
那你說OK這個
You found the gene that controls fruit wing development
你找到控制果營翅膀發育的基因
So what's so great
So what 有什麼了不起
Right, man has no wings
對不對 人又沒翅膀
What about in the fruit camp?
那在果營裡面呢
find a gene at the beginning
找到一開始的一個基因
It was later discovered that there is actually a series of such genes
後來就發現其實是有一系列這樣的基因
that and this set of genes is interesting
那而且這一系列的基因很有趣
the order in which it is arranged on the chromosome
它在染色體上面的排列的順序
is consistent with the order in which they affect body parts
跟他們影響身體部位的順序是一致的
This one affects the development of the first tone
這一個就影響最前面這個口氣的發育
Then this will affect the development of the tail
然後這個呢就影響最尾巴的發育
come in order
順序過來
Then such things exist in fruit flies
那這樣的東西就在果蠅裡面有
It is more interesting to find
更有意思的是發現
It's not just fruit flies
那其實不只是果蠅有
Assuming only fruit flies exist, I won't talk about it today
假設只有果蠅有我今天就不講
Then it's because in mice and in people
那它因為在老鼠在人
in various creatures
在各式各樣的生物裡面
have these genes
都有這些基因
There is a group of fruit flies
那在果蠅裡面有一群
In humans or mice there are four groups of these genes
在人呢或老鼠有四群這樣的基因
Then they basically correspond like this
那他們基本上是這樣對應
So basically if there are fruit flies, there are people too.
所以大致果蠅有 人就也有
It's just that people are a little more complicated, a little more
只是人比較複雜一點 更多一點
Even more interesting is the order in which they are arranged
更有趣的是他們排列的順序
It's roughly the same order as the fruit fly
也大致跟果蠅的順序是一樣的
So it means that the order must be important
所以表示這個順序一定很重要
So why does this order matter until now?
那一直到現在這個順序到底為什麼重要
Why is it left behind in evolution
為什麼在演化上會被留下來
Not very clear
還不是很清楚 眾說
Diverse
多紛紜
Then such a gene affects development in Drosophila
那這樣的基因在果蠅裡面影響發育
Are there any rats?
在老鼠有沒有
Then we see these genes
那我們就看到這幾個基因
Indicated here in different colors
這裡用不同的顏色表示
where they appear on the body
他們在身體上面表現的位置
that will affect
那就會影響
I just saw that fruit flies are body segments
剛好看果蠅是體節嘛
segmental passage
分節一節
So what kind of segmented structure do we humans have?
那我們人有什麼樣的分節的構造呢
The most obvious is our spine
最明顯就是我們的脊椎
The spine is divided into cervical, thoracic, lumbar, shoulder, and coccyx
脊椎分了頸椎、胸椎、腰椎、肩椎、尾椎
Every single one of these spines you take out to see
每一個這個脊椎骨您拿出來看
its shape is different
它的形狀都不太一樣
Especially the part of the thoracic spine
尤其這個胸椎的部分
I still need to grow this rib
還要長這個肋骨出來
The different genes are called Hox genes
那不同的這種基因叫Hox基因
it manifests itself in this
它就表現在這個
Different positions of the body from front to back
身體從前到後的不同的位置
that this is different
那這個不同的
It determines where you grew up
就決定了你那個位置長出來的
what kind of vertebra
是哪一類的脊椎骨
we watch mice
我們看老鼠
This cervical vertebra of the mouse is here
老鼠的這個頸椎是這裡
There are seven vertebrae
有七椎
What about chickens? There are so many cervical vertebrae.
那雞呢 同樣的頸椎就有這麼多
about a dozen sections
大概有十幾節
Then he has less thoracic spine
那他的胸椎比較少
And this mouse has more thoracic vertebrae
然後這個老鼠的胸椎比較多
The demarcation points of these cervical and thoracic vertebrae
那這些頸椎胸椎的分界點
These are the Hawks genes just mentioned
就是剛才講的這些Hawks基因的
expressive boundaries
表現的邊界
So these boundaries the range they represent
所以這些邊界他們表現的範圍
It determines what kind of bone will grow in this position
就決定了這個位置會長什麼樣的骨頭
Another place is
另外一個地方是
This is also Hawks content
這也是Hawks內容
13 or 11
13或者11
Then if under normal conditions
那假如正常的狀況之下
This is the metacarpal bone of a mouse
這是老鼠的掌骨
dye here
這裡染色
This red is dyed cartilage
這個紅色染的是軟骨
blue stained bones
藍色染的是硬骨
If this gene is broken
那這一個基因假如壞掉
Its development is slightly different
它的這個發育就稍微有一點不太一樣
If both genes are broken
假如兩個基因都壞掉
it becomes like this
它就變成這樣
It just doesn't grow the bones at the far end.
它就遠端的那些骨頭都長不出來
Mutation of another gene on mating
在配合上另外一個基因的突變
This is another one called Glycery
這是另外一個叫做Glycery
If there is something wrong with this gene
那這個基因假如出了問題
look at this time
你看這時候
fingers become more than five
指頭變成不只是五個
it has about seven to eight here
它這裡大概有七個到八個
Then if both genes are completely destroyed
然後假如兩個基因都完全破壞掉
it has thirteen fingers
它就有十三個指頭
And it's not as long as the front
而且都長不到前面
None of the remote
遠端的都沒有
So these genes affect the development of many different parts of our body
所以這些基因影響我們身體的很多不同部位的發育
Let me talk about the eyes again
再來我講一下眼睛
Then the facts of my own experiments study this eye
那我自己實驗的事實研究這個眼睛
This is restudy
這是復研
very beautiful very regular
非常的漂亮非常的規律
This was filmed with a wire
這是用電線拍的
This is an optical microscope
這種是用光學顯微鏡
Taken by Jiebo Microscope
潔波顯微鏡拍的
normal it is red
正常的它是紅色的
this one is a mutant it's white
這一個是個突變它是白色的
Because the arrangement of this eye is very regular
因為這一個眼睛它的排列非常的規律
so any small change
所以任何微小的變化
you can easily detect
你都可以很容易的偵測得到
So this is a
所以這就是一種
you see this and you think
你就看到這個你就覺得
the surface is very rough
表面就很粗糙
irregular
不規律
This is also a mutation
這也是一個突變
This is another mutation
這是另外一個突變
The whole eye is gone
整個眼睛就不見了
Then there is another mutation
那還有一個突變呢
his eyes got small
他的眼睛變得很小
and small he is
而且很小他是
from top to bottom like this
從上到下這樣一個
Straight
直條狀
So just look at the type
所以光從型態上面
we can see
我們就可以看得到
Various can affect the eyes
各種各樣會影響眼睛
developmental mutations
發育的這些突變
Then you can do it from here
那從這邊就可以去做
a lot of analysis
很多的分析
I think the funniest thing is
那我覺得最有趣的是
this one mutation
這一個突變
just said Eilus
就剛才講過Eilus
Then he mutated and the whole eye disappeared.
那他突變整個眼睛就不見了
So this means
所以這表示說
This gene is
這一個基因是
Necessary for secondary actor development
副演發育所必須的
If his eyes are broken, they won't grow back
他壞了眼睛就長不出來
that's more interesting
那更有趣的是
If this gene
假如把這一個基因
bring him to show on the wings
拿來讓他表現在翅膀上
or on the head
或者表現在頭上
he can be on the wings
他就可以在翅膀上
on the legs
腿上
On the legs, and then on this antennae, there are eyes
腿上 然後這個觸角上長眼睛
So without him, the eyes can't grow
所以缺了他眼睛就長不出來
Then you show him in that place
那你給他表現在那個地方
Just grow an eye
就長一個眼睛出來
So this gene determines
所以這個基因就決定
Do you want to develop into eyes?
要不要發育成為眼睛這件事情
decide his fate
決定他的命運
Then this experiment is a Swiss
那這個實驗是瑞士一個
A Water Garing made in his laboratory
一個Water Garing他實驗室做出來
Then you see the eyes are very beautiful
那你看這個眼睛長出來非常的漂亮
Then the same if this gene directly affects the effect
那同樣的假如這個基因直影響果影
i won't talk here
我也不會在這裡講
The same gene exists in both mice and humans
那同樣的這個基因在老鼠在人都有
In mice, this gene mutation is called small eyes.
那在老鼠呢這個基因突變叫做小眼
His eyes became smaller
他的眼睛就變了小小的
this is normal
這個是個正常的
What about human genes?
那在人呢這樣的基因呢
He doesn't have red membranes in his eyes
他就沒有 眼睛就沒有紅膜
The man, the mouse and the fly, this gene
那人 老鼠跟果蠅的這個基因
are very similar in structure
在結構上都很相近
So if this gene
所以假如這一個基因
It controls the development of the eyes
它是控制眼睛的發育
Some people say that this is called a master gene
那有人就說這個叫做一個master gene
it is master
它是主控
Then he decides whether the eyes should develop or not
那他決定眼睛要不要發育
That other study said
那另外的研究說
It takes about 2,500 genes to make an eye
做一個眼睛 大概要2500個基因參與
There is a very complicated process
有非常複雜的一個過程
So we can imagine saying
那所以我們可以想像說
This I-LUS this gene
這個I-LUS這個基因
it is a switch
它是一個開關
it turns on the whole
它開啟整個
a program of reenactment of development
復演發育的一個程式
a program
一個program
Well, someone did an experiment like this
好 那有人就做了一個這樣的實驗
he put human genes
他把人的基因
I just said that it is very similar to the genes of fruit flies
剛才說跟果蠅的基因很像
It is used in fruit ants to express
它就拿來到果蟻裡面去表現
Do exactly the same experiment as the fruit ants.
做跟剛才果蟻那個實驗完全一樣
what do you think will happen
那你認為會發生什麼事情
it turns out
結果就發現
Human genes are put in
人的基因放進來
put it in fruit ants
放到果蟻裡面表現
can still produce an eye
照樣可以產生一個眼睛
So the resulting eyes are the eyes of fruit ants
所以說這個產生出來眼睛是果蟻的眼睛
or human eyes
還是人的眼睛
What we put in is this switch
我們放進來是這個開關
it opens the city behind
它打開後面的這個城市
The whole city is still a city of fruit ants
整個城市還是果蟻的城市
So it grows out as the secondary eye of fruit ants
所以它長出來還是果蟻的副眼
This is very interesting, it means
這個很有意思,這表示說
It's been so long since evolution
演化上面隔了這麼久
The original switch is still in use
最早用的這個開關一直都還在用
Obviously this switch is very important, it cannot be changed randomly
顯然這個開關很重要,就不能夠亂變
So from fruit flies to people
所以從果蠅到人
Someone pushes it further to simpler organisms
有人再往前推到更簡單的生物
This gene was also found
發現也有這個基因
Some even push it all the way to single-celled organisms
甚至有人一直推到單細胞的生物
we won't talk about that
那個我們就不講
Anyway, there's a gene that matters
反正這有一個基因很重要
Then as long as you let this gene express
那只要這個基因你讓它表現
it makes an eye
它就做個眼睛
That power is a bit too much
那這個權力有點太大
In case it accidentally behaves wrong
萬一它不小心表現錯了
expressed in a cell
表現在某一個細胞
That one cell becomes the eye
那一個細胞就變成眼睛
then we should
那我們身上就應該
Inexplicably, there are some places with eyes
莫名其妙就會有一些地方長眼睛
but it didn't happen
可是就沒有發生
So our laboratory has done such an experiment
所以我們實驗室有做這樣的實驗
is that we found such a gene
就是我們發現這樣的基因
It actually manifests in the embryo
它其實在胚胎的時候表現
The location is not just where the eyes are
位置不只是在長眼睛的地方
it behaves elsewhere
它其他地方也會表現
Apparently in those places it doesn't cause eyes
顯然在那些地方它都不會造成眼睛
So it's not that it's that powerful
所以並不是說它權力那麼大 那麼powerful
In addition we can also in this
另外我們也可以在這個
On this tissue that will develop into wings in the future
將來要發育成為翅膀的這個組織上面
performance, for example, in such a circle
表現 譬如說表現在這樣一圈
It is only at this point that the cells of the eye are produced
只有在這一個點才會產生眼睛的細胞
So it doesn't spawn eyes everywhere
所以它並不是到處都會產生眼睛
Then such research can be said later
那這樣的研究後來就可以說
Then it must cooperate with other factors.
那它一定是要跟其他的因子一起合作才行
The one it wants to cooperate with only appears in this place
那它要合作的那個只在這個地方出現
So it's only in that place that it can produce eyes
所以它只有在那個地方才能夠產生眼睛
So this follow-up
所以這個後續
did a series of studies like this
就做了一系列這樣的研究
one of his collaborators
其中一個跟他合作的
It was our lab that found this gene called Igon
是我們實驗室找到這個基因叫做Igon
As the name suggests, this gene is also broken.
顧名思義也是這個基因壞掉
The eyes are gone, just gone
眼睛就不見了 就Gone
So he is very similar to Iless
所以他跟Iless是很相近的
Let's find out his genes
我們把他基因找出來
It is found that the structure is also very similar
發現結構上面也很像
But the two do different things
可是兩個做的事情是不一樣
Express the Iless gene in places other than the eyes
把Iless這個基因表現在眼睛以外的地方
he will have eyes
他就會長眼睛
But expressing the Igon gene in the body
可是把Igon這個基因表現在身體
He is still only next to the eyes
他還是只在眼睛的旁邊
can produce eyes
可以產生眼睛
But it doesn't work anywhere other than the eyes
可是眼睛以外的地方都不行
So he doesn't decide the fate of the eyes
所以他不決定眼睛的命運
This one decides the fate of the eyes
這一個決定眼睛的命運
But we want to add the two together
可是我們想要把這兩個都加在一起
I saw that every extra eye grew very big at this time
就看到這個時候每一個多出來的眼睛都長得很大
Then our experiments found that
那後來我們的實驗就發現
It turns out that the Eros gene controls developmental destiny
原來這埃羅斯基因它是控制發育的命運
Naegon, the gene that controls cell division
那埃岡這個基因是控制細胞的分裂
So if you want to generate eyes in this place
所以你假如在這個地方要產生眼睛
It has very few cells, so it grows very small
它只有很少的細胞那長出來就很小
But adding this one can increase the number of compound eye cells
可是加上了這一個它就讓復眼的細胞可以變多
so the eyes get bigger
所以眼睛就會變大
So normally both genes need
所以正常狀況之下兩個基因都需要
to produce a true compound eye
才能夠產生一個真正的復眼
From these studies of the eyes, we can also see
那從眼睛的這些研究我們也可以看到
There are various mutations that affect eye size
有各式各樣的突變會影響眼睛的大小
The normal eyes here just now are so big
剛才這邊這個是正常的眼睛是這麼大
Some mutations make the eyes smaller
有一些突變就讓眼睛小一點
more serious eye disappears
更嚴重一點的眼睛就不見
So this is to make the eyes smaller
所以這個是讓眼睛變小
There is another direction to make the eyes bigger
那有另外一個方向讓眼睛變大
At this time, the eyes become a little swollen
那這個時候眼睛就變得有點腫腫的
That's more serious and it becomes like this
那更嚴重就變成這樣
so it wrinkled
所以它皺起來
because it has too many cells
因為它的細胞太多
Then you can't become such a big
那你沒有辦法變成一個這麼大的
so it folds up
所以它就折起來
So that's a lot like cancer
所以那這個就跟癌症很像
grow a tumor
長一個腫瘤
So some people use fruit flies to study cancer
所以也有人用果蠅來研究癌症
Some people say that cancer has been studied for decades
那有人就說癌症已經研究了幾十年
So now you join in the research with fruit flies.
那你現在果蠅加進來做研究
Any chance of finding something new?
還有機會找到什麼新東西嗎
it did find
那確實就有找到
that's normal
那這是正常的
This is a mutation found
這是找到的一個突變
it overproliferates this cell
它會讓這個細胞過度增生
The growth area is very large
增生面積很大
so wrinkled like this
所以就這樣皺起來
This wrinkled look is a bit like a Shar Pei
這個皺起來的樣子有點像沙皮狗
basically an increase in surface area
基本上就是表面積增加
your body hasn't changed
你的身體沒有變
So it just has to fold the skin
所以它表皮就只好折起來
Shar Pei
沙皮狗
So this gene was originally called
所以這個基因最早就叫做
Shopey Sharpei
Shopey沙皮
Later, it was named earlier because of another person.
後來因為另外一個人命名比較早一點
So it's called Sovodor
所以就改叫Sovodor
This series of genes
這一系列的基因
Then I found out how they work
後來就知道他們是怎麼樣子運作
transmission of such a signal
這樣一個訊號的傳遞
from cell surface
從細胞表面
And then all the way to the cell river
然後一路傳到細胞河裡面
control gene expression
控制基因的表現
such a signaling chain
這樣一個訊號傳遞鏈
hyperactivation
假如說過度活化
will produce such a situation
就會產生這樣的狀況
it's a normal
這是一個正常的
A piece of tissue will develop into a wing in the future
一片組織將來要發育成為翅膀
If this HIPPO is excessive, it will become like this
假如這個HIPPO過度就變成一個這樣子
grow very big
就長得非常的大
Such a PASSWARE was first found in Drosophila
這樣一個PASSWARE在果蠅裡面最早被找出來
Then it was discovered that in the rat people there are
然後後來就發現在老鼠人都有
In experiments with mice
在老鼠的實驗裡面
If you overactivate this PASSWARE
假如你讓這一個PASSWARE過度活化
The whole liver becomes so big
整個肝就變成這麼大
Then in this signal transmission chain
那這一個訊號傳遞鏈裡面
There is a gene that is Selvador, Sarpy mentioned here
有一個基因是這邊講的Selvador,Sarpy
Another gene is called HIPPO
另外一個基因就叫做HIPPO
that's what makes this organization big
就是它讓這個組織變得很大
just like homer
就好像荷馬一樣
So this HIPPO PASSWARE was the first to be found in fruit flies
所以這一個HIPPO PASSWARE是最早從果蠅裡面找到
In the past in human cancer research
過去在人類的癌症研究裡面
did not find this one
沒有發現到這一個東西
Then this password is very important
那這一個password很重要
Because cancer takes a tumor to grow
因為癌症要一個腫瘤要長
He wants cell division
他一個是要細胞分裂
he will grow a lot
他要長很多
Then our body has some mechanism
那我們的身體有一些機制
you split too much
就是你分裂太多
i'm going to kill you
我就要把你殺掉
So the cell kills itself
所以這個細胞會自殺
After such a password is activated
那這樣一個password活化以後
On the one hand, he makes the cells divide more
他一方面讓細胞會多分裂
On the one hand, keep him from dying
一方面讓他不會死
So the one who was supposed to die didn't die
所以本來該要死掉的不死
So many and not dead
所以又多又不死
Then it becomes like this
那就變成這樣的狀況
so this is a
所以這是一個
used to study cancer is now a very important part
用來研究癌症現在非常重要的一個部分
that could do more cancer research
那還可以做更多癌症的研究
It's cancer, usually you have a tumor
就是癌症通常你長一個腫瘤
The tumor itself is usually not fatal
腫瘤本身通常不會致命
We can see news reports that
我們可以看到新聞報導說
A certain person has a 20-kilometer
某一個人身體裡面有一個20公里
It can also walk around with this 20 kilograms and live for a long time
它也可以帶著這20公斤走來走去活很久
fine
沒事
Unless the tumor just presses on your blood vessels or nerves
除非這個腫瘤剛好壓到你的血管或者神經
you will have problems
你才會出問題
What about the most common and deadly cause of cancer?
那癌症最常見會致命的原因呢
is it shifted
是它轉移了
It's not just a tumor
它就不是一個點的腫瘤
Instead, it travels to all parts of the body
而是它跑到身體各個地方
Attack more now
這個時候就多點攻擊
that's more serious
那就比較嚴重
Therefore, a very important aspect of our research on cancer is
所以我們對癌症的研究一個很重要的是
Inhibition of asking how this transfer occurred and what it looked like
問這個轉移是怎麼發生然後怎麼樣子的抑制
So someone did this beautiful experiment
所以有人就做這樣一個很漂亮的實驗
it puts part of the cells
它把一部分的細胞
make it express a cancer-causing gene
讓它表現一個致癌的基因
This is called RES
這個叫RES
After the performance, this small piece of tissue will proliferate a lot
表現以後這一小塊組織就會大量增生
grow up like this
就長成這樣
This kind of organization we call it
這種組織我們把它
and make it express a green fluorescent protein
同時讓它表現一個綠色螢光蛋白
so you can see this piece
所以你看得到這一塊
It's bright green and grows a lot
就是綠色亮亮的 長很多
but it won't run around
可是它不會亂跑
it stops here
它就停在這裡
So this is a normal tumor
所以這個就是一般的腫瘤
use such a basis
利用這樣的基礎
Then look for any genetic mutations
再去找有沒有什麼基因的突變
Let this one tumor start running around now
會讓這一個腫瘤現在開始亂跑
start transfer
開始轉移
For example, a new mutation is found here
譬如說這邊就找到一個新的突變
It will make this group now run to other parts of the body
它會讓這一群現在跑到身體其他的地方
Take out this piece of cells that will transfer
把這一塊會轉移的這樣的細胞拿出來
Transplanted into another fly
移植到另外一隻果蠅
found that it would continue to run around
就發現它也會繼續亂跑
So start this way
所以從這種方式開始
so we can find out which genes affect cancer cells
我們就可以找到哪些基因會影響癌症細胞
Will it transfer
會不會轉移
And then you can even screen for drugs
然後甚至你可以去篩選藥物
Another one is related to cancer.
再來一個也是跟癌症有關的
This is also a very unexpected thing that happened in basic research
這個也是很意外的基礎研究發生的一件事情
He found that if we put such a real organization
他就發現假如我們把這樣一個果然的組織
This piece will grow into wings in the future
這一片將來是要長成翅膀
go and x-ray it
去給它照X光
Then do some damage, some cells will die
那就造成一些傷害 有一些細胞就會死掉
So these cells with red dots and red dots have changed
所以這些紅點紅點的細胞就是發生了變化
will die
就會死掉
So after a while this gets smaller
所以過了一段時間這個就變小了
because those cells die
因為那些細胞死掉
then you give it time
然後這個你再給它時間
it will grow back to its normal size
它就會長回到原來正常的大小
it makes up for it completely
它就完全補回來了
So this is our body's normal repair of external damage
所以這個是正常我們身體對外來傷害的修復
What's interesting is that if in an experiment like this
那有趣的是假如在這樣的實驗當中
I'll take an X-ray of it
我給它照X光
the green half
綠色的這一半
I express a gene to
我表現一個基因去
make those damn cells
使得那些該死的細胞
won't die now
現在不會死
So some
所以就產生了一些
damn cell
該死不死的細胞
It turns out that this group of cells
結果發現這一群細胞呢
Blooming now
現在大量繁殖
become a large tumor
變成一個大的腫瘤
then from here
那從這裡就
derived a series of studies
得出了一系列的研究
the dead cell
那個死掉的細胞
dying cells
就是要死的細胞
it will send out a signal
它會放一個訊號出來
tell the next cell to say
告訴旁邊的細胞說
I'm going to say goodbye
我要拜拜了
make it up to me
你趕快彌補我
So there is an empty
所以這裡有個空
So you split up to make up for me
所以你趕快分裂來補我的缺口
Then if this group of cells is now
那假如這群細胞現在
damn it
該死不死
you let it stay there
你讓它一直停在那邊
It continues to play such a signal
它就繼續放這樣的訊號
So the cells next to it have a lot of rope
所以旁邊的細胞就大量繩繩
Then tell the side
那這個也就告訴旁邊
when we say we cure cancer
我們說我們治療癌症的時候
Usually you give me a medicine
常常就是你給個藥
kill that cancer cell
把那個癌細胞殺掉
the cells that kill
那些殺掉的細胞
if not quickly drained
假如沒有很快的被排掉
it actually sends a signal
它其實會釋放訊號
Let the next cell grow again
讓旁邊的細胞再長
so you kill the cells
所以你把這些細胞殺了
There are supplements on the side
旁邊都有補回來
So that cancer becomes unkillable
所以那個癌症就變成殺不完
So this becomes saying now
所以這就變成說現在
cancer treatment considerations
治療癌症需要考慮的
a very important thing
一個很重要的事情
So you see although fruit flies look
所以你看雖然果蠅看起來
so small
這樣小小的
But only on the matter of cancer
可是光在這個癌症的事情上面
It has many important new contributions
它就有很多很重要的新的貢獻
the other one
那另外一個
let everyone know
讓大家都知道
A hot topic is stem cells
很熱門的題目就是幹細胞
stem cell is a cell
幹細胞是一個細胞
then it will split
那它會分裂
become two cells
變成兩個細胞
these two cells
這兩個細胞
One of them will differentiate into other cells in the future
其中有一個將來就去分化成為別的細胞
The other one is himself
另外一個就是他自己
so he split forever
所以他永遠分裂分裂
He made himself up again
他就又把自己補回來
so I will never change
所以自己永遠不變
He keeps producing new cells to differentiate out
他一直產生新的細胞分化出去
This ability to self-renew is stem cells
這種自我更新的能力就是幹細胞
Stem cells often just sit there
幹細胞常常就停在那邊
when we come of age
到了我們成年
Stem Cells Might Stop Over There
幹細胞可能停在那邊
when you need it
碰到需要它的時候
it split
它才分裂
In studies of fruit flies, it was found that
在果蠅的研究裡面發現
Stem cells are influenced by the environment next to them
幹細胞會受到它旁邊的環境的影響
This is the stem cell
就是這個是幹細胞
it has some cells next to it
它旁邊有一些細胞
It will be controlled by certain signals
會經過某些訊號去控制它
Then once the stem cell divides
那這個幹細胞一旦它分裂
This stem cell is out of this environment
這個幹細胞就脫離了這個環境
it is not controlled so it differentiates
它就不受到控制 所以它就分化
It can't be differentiated if it's always connected here
一直連在這邊的它就不能夠分化
so it maintains the stem cells
所以它就維持幹細胞
So there are many experiments telling us that
所以就有很多的實驗告訴我們說
This Nich is called a seat
這個Nich 有人叫做席位
It is a microenvironment
它就是一個microenvironment
a small environment
一個小小的環境
this seat is important
這個席位很重要
The size of the seat determines how many stem cells
席位的大小就決定有多少幹細胞
can stay here
可以留在這邊
Seats got smaller
席位變小了
or as you get older
或者隨著年紀年老了以後
This Nich might get smaller and older
這個Nich 可能會變小 變老
Its ability to maintain stem cells becomes worse
它維持幹細胞的能力就變差了
so we reach old age
所以我們到了老年
Our stem cells also get worse
我們的幹細胞也會變差
So this seat it can control stem cells of trees
所以這個席位它可以控制幹細胞的樹木
it controls aging
它可以控制老化
stay here and go out
留在這邊和出去的
to form an appropriate proportion
要形成一個適當的比例
it goes out too much
它出去的太多
Your stem cells haven't stayed here yet
你這個幹細胞還沒有留在這邊
it also becomes differentiated
它就也變成了分化
it reduces the number of stem cells
它就幹細胞的數目就減少
so these are very important
所以這些都非常的重要
Then this microenvironment will affect stem cells
那這一個微環境會影響幹細胞
this nitch
這一個nitch
It was also first discovered in Drosophila
也是在果蠅裡面最早被發現
Then some people use fruit flies to study immunity
那也有人用果蠅來研究免疫
It puts fruit flies on it and puts some of this needle fungus
它把果蠅給它放一些這個針菌
Then this needle fungus will infect fruit flies
那這個針菌就會感染果蠅
then grow very fast
然後就長得很快
Like this fruit fly, its immune system has problems
像這支果蠅它的免疫力出問題
So it gets eaten quickly by the needle fungus
所以它很快就被針菌感染吃進去
So the same from here
所以同樣的從這裡
You can then screen for mutations
你就可以去篩選突變
There is no resistance to needle bacterial infection
對針菌感染現在沒有抵抗力的
or super resistant
或者說抵抗力超強的
Then a series of genes were found
然後就找到了一系列的基因
What's interesting about this set of genes?
那有趣的是這一系列的基因呢
It was later discovered that there are also
後來就發現在人也有
So this series of human grapes
所以人的葡萄類的這一系列
very close to fruit flies
跟果蠅非常的接近
So let's do some research with fruit flies
所以那就可以用果蠅來做一些研究
So because of this study this
那所以因為這個研究這個
Jules Hoffman in 2011
Jules Hoffman在2011
He won the Nobel Prize with two others
跟另外兩位合得了諾貝爾森利獎
It's also about disease
那還有跟疾病有關的
it's this fruit fly
是這一隻果蠅
This fruit fly was the first mutation found
這一隻果蠅是最早找到的一個突變
Then it's called Windless
那它叫做Windless
just no wings
就是沒有翅膀
It has such a mutation that both wings are missing
它有的這樣的突變是兩個翅膀都不見
some are missing a wing
有的是一個翅膀不見
like this one it's this side
像這一隻它是這一邊
The wings on this side are missing
這一邊的翅膀不見
The first gene was later studied a lot
第一個基因後來研究了很多
It plays an important role in all stages of development
他在發育的各個階段都扮演很重要的角色
He discovered that this gene is called Windless in the fruit camp
他就發現這個基因在果營叫做Windless
It is found in people that it is called Int1
在人就發現叫做Int1
is an early study of cancer that found one
是一個早期研究癌症找到的一個
genes associated with viruses
跟病毒有關的基因
So this gene was later called Wint
所以這一個基因後來就叫做Wint
Take this W and NT
取這個W和NT
This Wint Passway is very close to the fruit camp and people
這個Wint Passway在果營和人都是非常接近
It was later discovered that he developed with various
後來就發現他跟各種各樣的發育
All kinds of diseases are related
各種各樣的疾病都有關係
So you can even make a book
所以你看甚至可以出一本書
It is Winds Signaling in development and disease
就是Winds Signaling在發育和疾病當中
There are many similar
類似的還有很多
I found it from the fruit camp
就是從果營找到的
an interesting mutation
一個有趣的突變
Affects certain developmental processes
影響了某些發育的過程
It was later discovered that the matter involved
後來發現牽涉到的事情
his role
他扮演的角色
are very much related to human diseases.
都跟人類的疾病非常有關
Another one I saw recently
還有一個我看到最近
Someone did such an experiment
有人做這樣的實驗
Studying Diabetes Using Drosophila
就用果蠅來研究糖尿病
obesity
肥胖
heart disease
心臟病
He gave fruit flies this high-fat diet
他給果蠅吃這個高脂肪的食物
fruit flies become fat
果蠅就變得很肥
a lot of fat accumulation
脂肪累積很多
this accumulation
這個累積
Not only in his fat tissue
不只在他的脂肪組織
will also accumulate to other organizations
還會累積到其他的組織
just like people
那就跟人一樣
In this example inside
在這個例子裡面
he will accumulate to the heart
他就會累積到心臟
Then the heart accumulates too much fat
然後心臟累積了太多的脂肪
there will be some diseases
就會產生一些病變
this lesion
這個病變
like human heart disease
就跟人類的心臟病
a certain kind of like
某一類很像
So you can also use this
所以也可以用這種
to study some of the heart disease
來研究心臟病的一些
so he can find some genes
所以他就可以找到一些基因
will go
會去
affect the process
影響這樣的過程
In the last period of time, I will talk about this brain
那最後一段時間我來講這個腦
We can use fruit flies to study brain function
我們可以用果蠅來研究腦的功能
this is the first one
這個是最早一個
Also a professor at Caltech
也是在Caltech加州理工學院的教授
Seymour Banser
Seymour Banser
He was an important figure in early molecular biology
那他是早期分子生物學的一個重要人物
he was born a physicist
他是物理學家出生
Then he went to study the virus
然後他去研究病毒
That's a great contribution to molecular biology
那對分子生物學有很大的貢獻
Then to class 1960
然後到1960級
He just said it's done
他就說那做完了
Important questions are done
重要的問題已經做完了
so he's looking for something new to do
所以他要找新東西做
So he said I'm going to use fruit flies to study neurons
所以他就說我要用果蠅來研究神經
What about the nervous system of the fruit fly?
那果蠅的神經系統是怎麼樣
This is our human brain
這個是我們人的腦
There are about 10 to 11 times that nerve cells
大概有10的11次方可神經細胞
A mouse has 10 brains
老鼠的腦有10個
There are 10 to the 8th power
有10的8次方
That's all the brains of fruit flies
果蠅的腦就這麼一點點
There are 10 to the 5th power
有10的5次方
There is also a nematode
那還有一個線蟲
Proportionally above
照比例上面
You can't see that point at all
那個點根本你看不見
The nematode has 302 nerve cells
線蟲有302個神經細胞
very precise
非常精確
Nematodes are a very special research material
線蟲是一個很特別的研究材料
we know it very, very well
我們對它了解的非常非常透徹
but too simple
可是太簡單了
So fruit flies have 10 to the power of 5 neurons
所以果蠅有10的5次方的神經細胞
Compared to humans and mice
相對於人和老鼠來講
this is smaller
這個就是比較小
Then it is better to study
然後比較好研究
Then wait a minute to show everyone
那等一下要給大家看
Its behavior is quite complicated
它的行為又還蠻複雜的
So SIMO BANZER started
所以SIMO BANZER一開始
He said I came to find the mutation
他就說我來找突變
What mutations affect neurological function
有什麼突變會影響神經功能
Then he did a lot of different screening
那他做了很多的不同的篩選
This one is a biological clock
這一個是做生理時鐘
It puts fruit flies in a tiny tube
它把果蠅放在一個小小的管子裡面
This fruit fly will walk around
這果蠅就會走來走去
It has an infrared Motion Detector
它就有一個紅外線的這個Motion Detector
to detect whether the fruit fly has holes
就偵測到這個果蠅有沒有洞
So a hole here is a black spot
所以在這邊有洞就是一個黑點
This sidewalk is time
這個橫走就是時間
so you just watch
所以你就看
From this line above
從這上面這條線看過來
Been going down this fruit fly for a while
在一直下去這個果蠅有一段時間
been in the hole
一直不斷在洞
then for a while
然後有一段時間呢
almost banned
就幾乎都禁止
hole again for a while
又有一段時間都在洞
From this cycle is about 24 hours
從這個周期大概就是24小時
So fruit flies have a parity clock of almost 24 hours
所以果蠅有一個差不多24小時的省理時鐘
Almost half of the 24 hours it was in the hole
在24小時當中差不多有一半它是在洞
half of it is sleeping
有一半它在睡覺
Using this letter, it will do the screening
利用這一個信狀它就去做篩選
Then we got three mutants
然後就得到了三種突變種
The first is the Wu cycle
第一個是吳周期
It can move at any time of the day
它就一天當中隨時都可能動一動
The other one is a short period of 19 hours
那另外一個是短週期 19個小時
Then one is a long period of 28 hours
然後一個是長週期 28個小時
Then the last three mutations were found to be the same gene
那最後這三個突變都發現是同一個基因
that its a different mutation
那它不同的突變
So the same gene, this gene is called period or per
所以同一個基因 這個基因就叫做 period or per
From here, there are many people looking for
從這裡開始就有很多的人去找
These genes affect the biological clock
影響生理時鐘的這些基因
Then finally find a complex regulation like this
那最後就找到一個這樣的複雜的調控
Then such regulation in mice and humans
然後這樣的調控在老鼠跟人
Actually very close
其實都非常的相近
it's basically a negative feedback
它基本上就是一個負向回饋
It's just my things are slowly increasing
就是我這個東西多慢慢增加
After increasing it inhibits its own generation
增加以後它就抑制它自己的生成
it goes down
它就降下去
down to a degree
降下去到一個程度
it has no way to suppress its own generation
它就沒有辦法抑制自己的生成
it grows again, it grows again
它又開始長 又開始生成
so there is a cycle
所以就有一個週期
This cycle is about 24 hours
這週期就差不多是24小時
So now I know quite a lot about such a process.
所以對這樣一個過程現在知道的蠻多的
Our cycles are regulated by light
我們的週期是會收到光去調控
There is also light that will pass through a certain photosensitive rate of fire
這裡面也有光線會透過某一個感光射速
Then affect this passage
然後影響這一個passway
Similar to just now, some people also use that method to study the sleep of Guoying.
跟剛才類似的也有人用那個方法去研究果營的睡眠
it has different activities and sleep times
它有不同的活動和睡覺的時間
Various mutants can also be found
也可以找到各種各樣的突變種
From here you can find some genetic influences
從這裡就可以找到有一些基因影響
Then know where these genes act in the brain
然後知道這些基因是作用在腦的哪些位置
So if this goes wrong you won't be able to sleep
所以假如這個出了問題你就會睡不著
so start here
所以從這邊就可以開始
Just ask Deputy Wang
就跟王副問我說呢
how do we adjust the time difference
我們時差怎麼調
you sleep disorder
那你睡眠障礙
how to treat
怎麼樣子去治療
Start here with some
從這邊就可以開始有一些
have some help with this
有一些這個幫助
Then someone used fruit flies to learn and remember
再來有人用果蠅去做學習和記憶
Don't think fruit flies are stupid
你不要以為果蠅笨笨的
actually it's not bad
其實它還不錯
That's the first experiment
那這個是最早的一個實驗
it smells to fruit flies
它就給果蠅聞味道
you have two flavors
你有兩個味道
You give it a smell first
你先給它聞A
then give it an electric shock
然後就給它一個電擊
inside this pipe
這個管子裡面
you put fruit flies in
你把果蠅放進去
Then the outside of the pipe is the same way
然後管子外面是同往
so you give it flavor on the one hand
所以你一方面給它味道
give it an electric shock
一方面給它電擊
after those few times
那幾次以後
it learns
它就學會了
It combines this taste with
它就把這個味道和
Will be linked together by electricity
會被電這件事情連在一起
then you put it
然後你就把它
From this electric tube
從這個會電的管子
move to another tube
移到另外一個管子
Then give him two flavors to choose
然後給他兩種味道去選
Two flavors one A and one B
兩種味道一個A一個B
He knows that A will be electrocuted
他知道A會被電
He ran towards B
他就往B那邊跑
so he can learn
所以他可以學的會
and he still has memory
然後他還有記憶
because you can live for hours
因為你可以過幾個小時
Come back in a few days
過幾天再來測
His memory will slowly fade
他的記憶會慢慢慢慢衰退
so he remembers
所以他記得
can be found here
從這邊就可以找到
Many mutants can affect this memory
很多的突變種會影響這個記憶
Then know these genes
然後就知道這些基因
then probably know
然後大概知道
this sequence of their actions
他們的作用的這個順序
Sure enough, there are other studies
那從果然當還有其他的研究
the study of other organisms
其他生物的研究
We can now take this memory
我們現在可以把這個記憶
into several stages
分成幾個不同的階段
have short term memory
有短期記憶
mid-term memory
中期記憶
long term memory
長期記憶
Another memory is anti-anesthesia
還有一個記憶是抗麻醉
there are some memories
就是有一些記憶是
If something happens, then you anesthetize him
假如事情發生,然後你給他麻醉
When he wakes up he doesn't remember that
醒來他就不記得那件事情
Because after the incident he needed to go
因為事件發生以後他需要去
save him
把他存起來
If you were anesthetized for a period of time
假如存的那一段時間被你麻醉了
He can't save it, that memory is lost
他就沒辦法存,那個記憶就喪失了
So there are these different stages
所以有這些不同的階段
There are many studies to distinguish those different stages
那些不同階段是有很多的研究去分出來
including different mutants
包括有不同的突變種
Each affects memory at different stages
各自影響不同階段的記憶
So this way we can differentiate it
所以這樣我們就可以把它區分出來
That's the distinction we'll probably know by now
那區分出來我們現在大概會知道
at the location of this nerve cell connection
在這個神經細胞的連結的位置
what kind of changes happened
發生一些什麼樣的這些變化
The mechanism of this basic memory
那對這個基本記憶的機制
after some understanding
有一些了解之後呢
someone to develop
有人就去開發
Is there any medicine that can enhance memory
有沒有什麼藥是可以增強記憶力
It is also said that many genetic
也有人說發現很多遺傳
sexual intellectual disability
性的智能障礙
Those genes are now identified
那些基因現在被找出來
Discovery is related to these
發現都跟這些有關
So it might also be possible to use
所以這裡可能也就可以去用來
Solve some problems of mental retardation
解決智能障礙的一些問題
We now know a lot about the brain
那我們現在對腦的了解也很多
So in a causal brain
所以在一個果因的腦裡面
We know that memory passes through this organization
我們知道記憶是經過這一個組織
This is called a mushroom body
這個叫做蘑菇體
It's this red and green
它就是這個紅的綠的這樣
So it seems like the mushroom has one sticking out like this
所以好像蘑菇有一個這樣伸出來
Then it can be divided into many cells
那這裡面又可以分成很多的細胞
We roughly know which cells are in which stage of memory
我們大概知道哪個細胞在記憶的哪一個階段
what role to play
扮演什麼樣的角色
Academician Jiang Anshi of Tsinghua University
那清華大學江安士院士
he did some experiments
他做了一些實驗
he said long term memory
他說長期記憶
There are two cells here that are very important
這裡面有兩顆細胞非常重要
The fake two cells don't work
假的那兩顆細胞不作用
Your long-term memory won't be able to form
你的長期記憶就沒有辦法形成
So we now have a function of these neurons
所以我們現在對這些神經的功能
Can know very, very finely
可以知道的非常非常的精細
Another interesting thing is
那還有一個很有趣的是
Drosophila's Wine Book
果蠅的酒冊
Someone made a design like this
那有人做了一個這樣的設計
He took many funnels and stacked them together
他拿了很多的漏斗疊在一起
Then pass the alcohol vapor through
然後把酒精的蒸氣通過去
put fruit flies on it
那把果蠅放在上面
fruit fly trap drunk
果蠅夾喝醉了
he just fell
他就掉下去
If you are not drunk at all
那假如完全沒有醉
He is standing on top of the drunk
他就站在醉上面
if a little drunk
假如有點醉
He just dropped one floor, two floors
他就掉一層 掉兩層
So you just see how many layers he dropped
所以你就看他掉了幾層
You can tell how drunk he is
就可以說他醉的程度是怎麼樣
So there is a very bright observation
所以有一個非常亮化的觀察
The same can be used to screen for mutant species
那同樣的可以去篩選突變種
that also said
那也有說
This looks like a wine book
這個好像真的是酒冊
Just give him a long tube and let him go
就是給他一個長長的管子讓他走
That also passes through alcohol vapour.
那同樣通酒精蒸氣
then you use
然後你就用
this camera to take pictures
這個攝影機去照
You can analyze whether its steps are messed up
你就可以分析它步伐有沒有淋亂
can you walk in a straight line
能不能夠走一直線
Then here is to see if alcohol is addictive
那這裡就是看酒精會不會成癮
It fills the capillary with water
它把毛細管裡面裝了水
there is plenty of water
那有的是水
some water plus alcohol
有的是水加上酒精
Then you can choose
然後你可以去選
Then it puts a different salt
那它放了不同的鹽料
So one is blue and one is red
所以一個是藍的一個是紅的
You just eat it last and look inside its stomach
你就最後吃看它肚子裡面
more blue or more red
藍的多還是紅的多
you know which one it likes
你就知道它會喜歡哪一種
Let's see if it's addictive to alcohol
那就看它是不是會對酒精上癮
There is an interesting experiment that says that
有一個很有趣的實驗說那個
If the public courtship is rejected,
假如公國營求偶被拒絕以後
then it will drink
那它就會敘酒
There are two students from Hsinchu Experimental Middle School
那有兩個新竹實驗中學的學生
Come to me for an experiment
到我那邊做實驗
he does that
他就做那個
they repeat that experiment
他們重複那個實驗
Turns out they didn't quite
結果他們發現不完全是這樣
After being denied state leave
公國營假被拒絕以後
at first he was very depressed
一開始他是很沮喪
he doesn't drink anything
他什麼都不喝
But if at this time he still drinks occasionally
可是假如這時候他偶爾還是會去喝
After he drank alcohol
他就喝到酒精以後
he started to like
他就開始喜歡
So there are two stages
所以是有兩階段
start with frustration
先開始是沮喪
and then a sobriety
然後是戒酒交仇
Such research is very important
這樣的研究非常的重要
because all over the world
因為在世界各國
especially alcohol or drug addiction in the United States
尤其美國酒精或者藥物的成癮
is very serious
是非常嚴重
So you can use this to do research
所以可以用這種去做研究
The state also has neurodegeneration
國營也有神經退化
So there are a lot of mutants
所以這有很多的突變種
he has these holes in his brain
他的腦就有這些空洞
Similar to our neurodegeneration
跟我們人類的神經退化也很像
So these genes are now being identified one by one
所以這些基因一個一個現在被找出來
this is a normal brain
這個是正常的腦
we can also put him
我們也可以把他
Take some of these genes that are already known to cause neurodegeneration in humans
把一些在人類已經知道會造成神經退化的這些基因
Take it and put it in the fruit fly to express
把它拿來放在果蠅裡面去表現
So you see this is a normal fruit fly
所以你看這個是正常的果蠅
This is if a human disease-causing gene is put into it
這個是假如把一個人類的這種致病的基因放進去
has become like this
已經就變成這樣
It's basically a lot of cells dying
它基本上就是很多的細胞都死掉了
So the red pigment is gone
所以紅色的色素不見了
And then there are these plaques left by dead cells
然後有這些死掉細胞留下來的斑
When you see eyes like this, they become very small
你看到像這個眼睛就變得很小
most cells die
大部分細胞都死掉
So from here we can study neurodegeneration
所以可以從這裡去研究神經的退化
There is also a type of picture that is very similar to our epilepsy
也有一類的這個圖片跟我們的癲癇很像
These pictures are very interesting
這一類圖片非常有意思
It's called BandSensitive like this
它的名字像這個叫做BandSensitive
This is called Knockdown
這個叫Knockdown
This picture is usually fine
這個圖片平常好好的
You hit its tube hard on the table
你把它的管子在桌子上用力一強
it just falls down
它就通通掉下來
Some will start to draw like this
有的就會這樣開始抽序
So just like our point display
所以就像我們的這個點顯一樣
then it's been a while
那它過一陣子呢
it will slowly recover
它會慢慢的會復原
in the process
在這個過程當中
This sequence is similar to the onset of human dots
這個序列跟人的點顯的發作
The process seems to be very similar
那個過程好像很像
So this set of these genes
所以這一系列的這些基因呢
Many people are now researching
現在很多人開始在研究
Sure enough, the names of these genes are very interesting.
那果然的這些基因的名稱都非常的有趣
You see this is called Knockdown
你看這個叫做Knockdown
This is called Eastly Shot
這個叫做Eastly Shot
easily scared
很容易被嚇到
This is Technical Knockout
這個是Technical Knockout
It's a technical knockout in boxing
就是拳擊上面的技術擊倒
This is called Couch Potato
這個叫做Couch Potato
it just sits there
它就坐在那邊不動
Different kinds
各種各樣的
Then our current research on the brain
那我們現在對腦的這個研究
very very fine
非常非常的精細
Then it can be in this brain
那它可以在這一個腦裡面
ten to the power of five cells
十的五次方的細胞
It turns only one of the cells green at a time
它一次只讓其中一顆細胞變成綠色
it can draw its this position
它可以畫出它的這個位置
where are these extensions of it
它的這些延伸在哪裡
Then it made tens of thousands of
然後它就做了幾萬個
Hundreds of thousands of such samples
十幾萬個這樣的sample
The accumulation wants to know the whole brain
那累積想要知道整個腦裡面
The relative position of each cell
每一顆細胞的相對位置
So this is something we'll know soon
所以這個是很快我們就可以知道
The structure of the whole brain of Drosophila
果蠅的整個腦的結構
Then we know the structure of these nerve cells
那我們知道這些神經細胞的結構
to go one step further and try to control it
還要更進一步想要去控制它
So someone developed this called
所以有人發展了這個叫做
Optogenetics
Optogenetics光譯傳學
it's inside certain nerve cells
它在某些神經細胞裡面
Express some special genes
表現一些特別的基因
This gene responds to light
這個基因對光會產生感應
so we use a different light
所以我們用不同的光
can turn off or activate this neuron
就可以讓這一個神經細胞關掉或者活化
So you can do something like this in the fruit camp
所以在果營裡面就可以做這樣的事情
This is also an experiment in Jiaen Temple
同樣這也是嘉恩寺的一個實驗
its under the microscope
它在顯微鏡底下
This has a plate inside and two nuts
這有一個盤子裡面和兩隻果營
it uses lasers to track
它用雷射去追蹤
have this camera
有這個攝影機
so it can track every fruit
所以它可以追蹤每一隻果營
the direction it goes
它走的方向角度
Which foot lifts up
哪一隻腳抬起來
which wing move
哪一個翅膀動一下
Everything can be analyzed
統統都可以分析
Then the following may not be able to put
然後下面這個可能沒有辦法放
it's here
它在這個這裡
come back
回來一下
It's two fruit flies, a bee, and a gnat
它兩隻果蠅 一隻蜂的 一隻蠂的
The bee will chase the bee
蜂的就會去追蜂的
This is normal courtship behavior
這是正常求偶行為
It makes the bee close to a certain distance from the bee
它就讓這個蜂的靠近蜂的某一個距離
just give it a pad
它就給它墊一下
It's not a pad it's a light burn it
它不是用墊 它用光燒它一下
Burned, this laser burns fruit flies will hurt
燒了 這個雷射燒了果蠅就會痛
So it will learn that it can't get close to this fruit fly
所以就會學到說它不能夠靠近這個果蠅
look here it will light up
你看這裡會亮一下
it's too close so light up
它太靠近了 所以亮一下
it goes away
它就走開
light up again
等一下又亮一下
you see it and run away
你看它就會逃開
After training like this for a while
這樣訓練一段時間之後
you come to test again
你就再來測試
Didn't pad him one female and one male
沒有去墊他 一隻母的 一隻公的
If the mother gets close to him, he will run away
母的靠近他 他就趕快逃
look at
你看看
so this
所以 這個
The duke will learn and you can train him
公國營就會學會 你可以訓練他
He knew that it would not work if he got close to a certain distance.
他就知道說 靠近到某一個距離就不行了
he will be burned
他會被燒
In that case, we can use this system to ask
那這樣的話 我們就可以 他就再用這個系統去問
So which nerve cell is related to this matter?
那到底是哪一個神經細胞跟這件事情有關
So you can decide what kind of neural circuit
所以就可以去決定說 哪什麼樣的神經迴路
to control such behavior
去控制這樣的行為
That's probably the last example
那這大概是最後一個例子
This is state-run and can also be used to study long pets
這是國營也可以用來研究長寵
There is only one state run called Mesucela
只有一隻國營叫做 Mesucela
this is a
這個是個
This is a normal fruit fly
這個是正常的果蠅
this is its lifespan
這是它的壽命
cross elbow is time
橫肘是時間
number of days
天數
Then how much is the vertical elbow alive?
然後縱肘是活下來多少
So it's 100% from the beginning
所以一開始都是百分之百
Then slowly some die
然後就慢慢慢慢有一些死掉
eighty days
到了八十天
just die
就全部死光
this is normal
這是正常的
What about the Messerlada fruit fly
那這個Messerlada果蠅
eighty days
到了八十天
more than half of it is still alive
它還有一半以上的還活著
that most often survives
那最常可以活到
more than one hundred days
一百多天
So why is it called Messerlada?
那為什麼叫做Messerlada呢
because this is
因為這個是
oldest person in the bible
聖經上面年紀最老的一個人
tell him to live
叫他活到
Nine hundred and sixty-nine years old
九百六十九歲
just make an appointment
就約上面
at that time
那個時候的
I don't know if it's exactly the same year as we are now
年跟我們現在不知道是不是完全一樣
anyway it's documented
反正這是有記錄
think the oldest
認為最老的
So this one is called Messerlada
所以這個就叫做Messerlada
that's very interesting
那非常有趣就是
it lives long
它長壽
But
可是
and at the same time
而且同時
It's an anti-tumor drug
這是一種殺腫藥
then it works against muscle
然後它可以抗肌肉
it can withstand high temperature
它可以抗高溫
So these resistance to stress are related to longevity
所以這些抵抗 stress 跟長壽是相關的
there is an important point here
那這邊有一個重點
It's a broken gene
這是一個基因壞掉
This picture is to make this gene broken
這個圖片是讓這個基因壞掉
As a result it grows longer
結果它變長壽
This means that the normal function of this gene
這表示說這個基因正常的功能
to keep you from living so long
是讓你不要活那麼久
So tell us about the design of this creature
所以告訴我們說這個生物的設計
You may have passed a useful point in evolution
演化上你可能過了某一個有用的時期
you should not go on living
你就不應該再繼續活下去
So it has a genetic design
所以它就有基因的設計
just let you die
就讓你會死掉
Then let's go back and destroy that gene
那我們忍回去把那個基因給它破壞
You can live longer as a result
結果你就可以活更久
And it doesn't just live long
而且它不只活很久
it's still healthy
它還很健康
Then of course this becomes
那這個當然就變成
Many people are very interested
很多人就非常的感興趣
you know this...
你知道這...
this is a receptor
這是一個受體
This is a GPCR receptor
這是一個GPCR的受體
it's on the surface of the cell
它在細胞的表面
So it must be receiving some signal
所以它一定是接受某些訊號
So this signal
所以這個訊號
Later, this signal in the body was also found
後來在體內的這個訊號也找到了
someone to design one
有人就去設計一個
Inhibition of such a segment of this receptor
抑制這個受體的這樣的一段
a period of ecology
一段生態
PEPTI
PEPTI
Such an inhibitory fruit fly eats
這樣一個抑制性的給果蠅吃下去
Its lifespan can also be extended
它的壽命也就可以延長
Then this gene is also present in humans
那這一個基因在人也有
So apparently someone is doing it right now
所以顯然有人現在正在做
How to increase human life span
怎麼樣子可以增長人類的壽命
from fruit flies and from mice
那從果蠅還有從老鼠
And from the worms just mentioned
還有從剛才講的現蟲
Some people are studying these genes of longevity
都有人去研究長壽的這些基因
Discovery of the mechanism of this lifespan regulation
發現這個壽命的調控的機制
These different creatures actually have one thing in common
這些不同的生物其實都是共通的
So do research with simple biology
所以用簡單的生物做研究
Of course it is more convenient and faster
當然要比較方便要快
So in the end it's
所以最終講到就是
We can use fruit flies to study some things about people
我們可以利用果蠅來研究人的一些事情
including development including disease
包括發育 包括疾病
Traditionally, we depend on the sky for food
傳統上面我們就是靠天吃飯
we filter
我們就篩選
These mutations occur randomly
隨機發生的這些突變
some is what we want
有的就是我們想要的
You find the mutation, you find the gene
你找到突變就可以找到基因
then do research
然後就去做研究
We can now do the reverse
我們現在可以做反向
That is, many genes we already know
就是很多的基因我們是已經知道
maybe from people
也許從人來
we can target this gene
我們就可以針對這個基因
to create specific mutations
去製造特別的特定的突變
To simulate some human diseases
去模擬人的一些疾病
From these we can understand
從這些都讓我們可以去了解
The function of these genes
這些基因的功能
Learn about the genes they regulate
了解他們的調控的基因
Only after you understand these basic things
只有在你了解這些基本的東西之後
Only you have the means to find a way to treat it and change it
你才有辦法去想辦法去治療它 去改它
So from here we can get the mechanism of healing
所以從這邊我們就可以到治病的機制
Strategies for treatment, even using fruit flies to screen for drugs
治療的策略 甚至用果蠅來做篩選藥物
fruit flies are fast and cheap
果蠅就快 便宜
It also allows us to deeply understand the mechanism
又可以讓我們很深入的去了解機制
But in the end, fruit flies are not people.
可是最後要強調果蠅不是人
Therefore, the drugs screened out by fruit flies may not be effective in humans.
所以果蠅篩出來的藥物到人不一定會有效
it has good reference value
它有很好的參考價值
But the final experiment still needs to be done by people.
可是最後的實驗還是要到人
Or its not easy for humans to conduct experiments, so we need to use creatures that are closer to humans to do it.
或者人不好做實驗要用比較接近人的生物去做
It is interesting to give an example at the end
最後舉一個例子很有趣
This is an old friend of mine Ross Kagan
這是我一個老朋友Ross Kagan
He was also the first to do eye development in Drosophila
他也是最早做果蠅的眼睛的發育
In recent years, he said that he would come for personal medical treatment
他最近幾年他說他要來搞個人醫療
He was a cancer patient
他就從癌症的病人
Then I found your tumor
那我找到你的這個腫瘤
I can sequence and know which genes are mutated
我可以定序知道裡面哪些基因發生突變
Then I put this mutant gene into fruit flies to express
然後我就把這個突變的基因放到果蠅裡面去表現
So I'm basically replicating your disease in fruit flies
所以我基本上就在果蠅裡面複製你的疾病
So he called this the Avatar of Fruit Flies
所以他把他這個叫做果蠅的阿凡達
this stand-in
這個替身
So this fruit fly has certain mutations
所以這個果蠅就帶有某些突變
It fully reflects the condition of that patient
完全反映了那一個病人他身上的狀況
Then he targets this person
然後他就針對這個人
These are the fruit flies that are used for drug screening
這些才就用這個果蠅去做藥物的篩選
drug screening
那他的藥物篩選
He said I don't want to find new medicine
他說我不要再去找新藥
There are already so many medicines
已經有那麼多種藥
Every medicine has side effects
每一種藥都有副作用
So medicine often does not mean whether you can kill cancer cells
所以藥常常不是說你能不能夠殺死癌細胞
How much damage do you do besides the cancer cells
除了癌細胞以外你還造成多少傷害
So he said I'd use a lower dose
所以他說我用劑量低一點
Then I take three medicines and five medicines together
然後我三種藥五種藥一起用
Every dose is low
每一個劑量都低
So his side effects are also low
所以他的副作用也低
Then I thought there might be several mechanisms
那還認為可能有好幾個機制
So I heal every mechanism
所以我每一個機制我都把它醫治掉
So this is for the condition of this patient
那這樣子針對這一個病人的狀況
he can do large-scale screening
他就可以做大規模的篩選
Then find a certain combination of drugs
然後就找出來某一種藥物的組合
kinda like cocktail therapy
有點像雞尾酒療法
for this patient
針對這個病人
I don't know if this is successful yet.
那這個到現在是不是成功還不知道
but an interesting attempt
可是一個蠻有趣的嘗試
And he's in New York, he's looking for that rich guy
而且他在紐約他就找那個有錢人
Many rich people get sick
有錢人很多得了病
are willing to invest in such a thing
都很願意投資做這樣的事情
So he has quite a few patients who are currently
所以他有蠻多的病人現在正在
doing these tests
在做這些測試
Maybe soon we will know this one strategy
也許很快我們就會知道這一種策略
will it work
會不會有效
This strategy is also due to the fact that in Drosophila
這個策略也是因為在果蠅裡面
You can do it cheaply enough at scale
你可以大規模做夠便宜
I will simply introduce to you today
我今天就很簡單的跟大家介紹一下
What kind of research can fruit flies be used for?
果蠅可以拿來做什麼樣的研究
I hope everyone knows
希望大家知道說
Why is there a group of people who like to play fruit flies so much
為什麼有那麼一群人很喜歡玩果蠅
it's cute
它是很可愛的
Finally, thank you all
最後就謝謝大家
Many thanks to our Dr. Sun for his excellent speech
非常感謝我們的孫博士的精采演講
I've seen a lot of people raise their hands
我已經看到有很多人舉手
So let's open some Q&A
所以我們就開放一些Q&A
come please
來 請
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
謝謝老師精采的演講
but very sorry
但是非常抱歉
The question I want to ask is
想要請問的問題是
so
所以
Why on earth did you abandon your wife?
到底為什麼會拋棄太太一刻念志愈
But what I want to ask the teacher more is
但是更想要請教老師的是
The teacher himself said in the speech that it is very annoying and enjoyable
老師自己在演講裡面講很討厭過癮
But it's been so many years
但是明明又做了這麼多年
So how does the teacher know when he encounters something he hates?
所以老師遇到討厭的怎麼知道
This is what I will do in the future
這個是自己將來要做的事
Then decide what you want to do in the future
然後確定自己將來要做的事
How to get over the nasty feeling
又怎麼克服討厭的感覺
I think many people want to know besides me
我想除了我以後很多人想知道
please thank you
就麻煩你謝謝
good
好
I'm interested in genetics
我對遺傳很有興趣
So when I was a freshman in high school, I decided to
所以我高中高一的時候我就已經決定要
Do basic biological research
做基礎生物研究
Then I am interested in genetics, so the candidate department
那我對遺傳有興趣所以那時候選系
I went to see some departments related to biology.
我就去看了生物相關的一些科系
I'm not particularly interested in plants
我並不是特別對植物有興趣
But the heredity of plant lineage is very much
可是植物系的遺傳非常多
They have a lot of lessons on genetics
他們的遺傳方面的課很多
No need to learn a second foreign language
還不用修第二外國語
So I chose the plant department
所以我就選了植物系
In the Department of Botany, I took a lot of courses on genetics
在植物系裡面我就修了很多遺傳方面的課
At that time, fruit flies gave me the feeling that it was a very traditional thing.
那那個時候果蠅給我的感覺就是很傳統的東西
decades ago
幾十年前的
So I went to Caltech
所以我去了加州理工學院
People say that you choose the laboratory
人家就說那你選實驗室
Someone recommended me this fruit fly laboratory
有人就跟我推薦這個果蠅的實驗室
I will talk about the Seamwater Benser later
就後面我講那個Seamwater Benser
Then my immediate reaction was this old-fashioned thing
那我一時的反應就是這老吊牙的東西
i have no interest
我毫無興趣
After studying for a few years, I read a lot of these papers
那後來念了幾年以後看了很多這些論文
I just knew that fruit flies are great stuff for a lot of things
我就知道果蠅是有很多東西可以做是非常好的材料
Then when I was doing my postdoc
然後我去做博士後的時候
I also want to say that I will return to Taiwan in the future.
也是想說將來要回台灣
Think fruit flies are cheaper
覺得果蠅是比較便宜的
At that time, I wanted to say that if I go back to Taiwan and have no money
那時候想說我回台灣萬一沒錢
At that time, Taiwan had no money
那時候台灣沒錢
Just wanted to say you can afford bananas
就想說可以買得起香蕉
I have a microscope and I can do research
我有個顯微鏡我就可以做研究
Then once you feel that the question you want to ask
那一旦你覺得你想要問的那個問題
Using fruit flies is a good material
用果蠅是個好材料
Those who don't like it will admit it
剩下那些不喜歡就認了
The microscope will make you dizzy
那顯微鏡看了會頭暈其實
just learn how to see
學會怎麼看就好了
I watch eight hours a day
我後來一天看八小時
Then it got better and better
後來也越來越好
So there's more to do
所以可以做的事情就更多
come on the one behind
來 後面那位
please teach me
請教一下
It was in the process of the complete metamorphosis
就是在果然的那個完全變態的過程中
Except for that knot that didn't change
除了那個節節沒有變出來
Is there anything that hasn't changed?
還有沒有什麼東西沒有變
such as organs or neurobrains
比如說器官或者是神經腦
Are you perverted?
有沒有變態
Then the second question is that
那第二個問題就是那個
Do householders have any advantages over those in the past?
戶人相對於當年有沒有什麼樣的優勢
That is to say, why is he really a developer?
就是說為什麼果然他是發展師出戶人
Instead of the development book
而不是發展書當年
After this family member mutated
這個戶人變異之後
growing in other parts of the whole
長在整體的其他部分
I think it works like this
是覺得作用這樣
ok what is the first question
好 第一個問題是什麼
That's totally perverted
那個果然完全變態
this is very interesting
這個很有意思
That is, if he completely knocks out the rework
就是 假如他完全打掉重作
You might want to call him a different entity
你就可能要叫他是不同的個體
He actually preserved his central nervous system
事實上他是保留了他的中樞神經系統
His brain is not knocked out
他的腦是沒有打掉
But the brain has also changed a lot
可是腦也發生很大的變化
a big change in his behavior
他的行為發生很大的變化
part of his digestive tract is preserved
他的消化道保留了一部分
also changed a lot
也是發生很大的變化
But still change him on the basis of the original
可是還是在原來的基礎上面給他改變
those cells on the surface of many other bodies
很多其他的身體的表面的那些細胞
Just kill it and rebuild it
就是完全殺掉 重新打造
so it was a very interesting process
所以那非常有趣的一個過程
the second is
第二個是
that encore
那個復演
Reenactment and solo performance
復演跟單演
Sure enough, there are reprises and solo performances
果然有復演 也有單演
There are three solo stars on his head
他的頭頂有三顆單演
What you see on the two sides is not the same
那兩邊看到的不太一樣
The monocular is very small so it basically has no resolution
單眼很小 所以它基本上沒有什麼解像力
Those eyes are bigger
那副眼就比較大
Then its area can be seen from a very large angle
然後它這個面積可以看的角度很大
Just now there was a very interesting Wang Fu mentioned
那剛才有一個很有趣的王富提到
It's that Guoying's eyes are red.
就是果鷹那個眼睛是紅色的
But this red is not a photosensitive pigment
可是這個紅色並不是感光的色素
It has about 800 ommatidia in its secondary eye
它的副眼裡面大概有800個小眼
Each ommatidium is a long tube structure
每一個小眼都是一個長筒的構造
The structure of the long tube is surrounded by pigment cells
長筒的構造周邊有色素細胞
is to express this red
就是表現這個紅色
So light can't get in from the side
所以光線從側面進不來
can only come in straight
只能夠從直直的進來
This means that it is on a spherical auxiliary eye
這樣的意思說在一個球面的副眼上面
every ommatidium every single eye
每一個小眼 每一個單眼
Seeing from a certain angle in space
看到的是空間中某一個角度
So as long as the monocular has light coming in
所以只要這個單眼有光線進來
It knows from which angle in the space the light comes in
它就知道空間中是哪一個角度進來的光線
As for the difference between reenactment and our eyes
至於復演跟我們這種眼睛有什麼差別
also difficult to analyze
也很難分析
But reenactment appeared very, very early in evolution.
可是復演在演化上出現的時間非常非常的早
In the three night insects, that is, inside the painted stone
在三夜蟲 就是畫石裡面
Trinite bugs have the structure of repetition
三夜蟲就有復演的構造
In fact, another question is
其實問到另外一個問題就是
when you fuck him
你們去操弄他的時候
Let's say another pair of reenactments
比如說產生了另外一對復演
Can the other reenactment be seen?
另外那對復演也看得見嗎
Is it a functional reenactment?
是有功能的復演嗎
same with wings
翅膀也是一樣
he has four wings can he fly
他有四個翅膀他會飛嗎
still he can't
還是他沒有辦法
coordinate
coordinate
Well, I don't know about the wings
好 翅膀那個我不知道
probably not good
大概是不太行
But it's a repeat, it grows on the wings and it's a repeat
不過復演 在翅膀上長得復演
If you poke an electrode in
你假如他戳一個電極進去
then give him a light
然後給他個光
he'll have a reaction, a normal reaction
他就會有反應 正常的反應
So that photoreceptor cell is normal
所以那個感光細胞是正常的
It grows in the position of the body, the brain is far away
它長在身體的位置 腦離得很遠
So its axis map can't be connected to the brain to connect
所以它的軸圖沒有辦法連到腦去接起來
So your brain doesn't feel the light.
所以你這邊照光 腦是沒感覺的
The brain does not receive the signal
腦接收不到訊號
But just now you also mentioned
不過剛才你也有提到
Is its photosensitive color different from ours?
它的感光色是不是跟我們人不一樣
Are we red yellow blue or red green yellow
我們是紅黃藍是不是 還是紅綠黃
anyway it's going to fall outside the line
anyway 它會感入依之外線
it has a green
它有一個綠色
There's a blue pigment and then there's an ultraviolet pigment
有一個藍色的色素 然後有一個紫外線的色素
so different
所以不太一樣
it's not red
它沒有紅的
There seems to be a problem just now
剛才好像有問題
green place
綠色的地方
Hello, teacher
老師您好
just put one
就是剛剛有放一張
Photos of Cang Ying's state camp chaos
倉穎 國營亂的照片
Then its right weight seems to be according to its
那它的右重似乎就是按照它的
it has a major axis
它是有一個長軸
So it was decided when it was still fertilized
所以就還受精的時候就已經決定
How does his body plan grow
他的body plan是要怎麼長的
Isn't it just a matter of accepting him?
是不是不單純只是受他的
I forgot what the name of that hormone is
我忘記那個激素的名稱叫什麼
The effect is that the hormone will also cause fertilization
的影響還是那個激素也會造成受精緣
It is the structural change inside a single cell
就是單個細胞的裡面的結構變化
well this is a very important question
好這是一個很重要的問題
There are many people in the state-owned enterprise doing such research
在國營裡面有很多人做這樣的研究
It's how the head and tail of your body are determined
就是你身體的頭尾到底怎麼決定
Let's see before the egg is fertilized
我們看那個卵還沒有受精之前
In fact, his shape is already different
其實他的形狀就已經有不一樣
So there are fronts and backs and burdens
所以就有前有後有背負
So this means that part of the decision
所以這表示說這一部分的決定
The body axis decision is already decided when the mother
體軸的決定是在媽媽時候就已經決定了
how does mom control
媽媽怎麼控制
Then a lot of genes control this matter
那就一大堆的基因去控制這件事情
before and after
那前後大政
it is consistent with mother's
它是跟媽媽的前後一致
The back and belly are random
那背和腹是random是隨機的
But when the egg was formed
可是在那個卵形成的時候
These have already been settled
這些就已經先定下來
its this egg
它的這個卵
Does a female eagle have only one egg?
一隻母鷹只有一個卵嗎?
or is it?
還是是?
it can lay eggs continuously
它可以不斷的下蛋
Can lay about two to three hundred eggs
可以下大概兩三百個蛋
it's a lifetime
它一輩子
almost
差不多
good nutrition
營養好的話
It can lay an egg in an hour
它一個小時就可以下一個蛋
So it's not the same as a crab
所以它跟螃蟹不一樣
crab words
螃蟹的話
it is soft is one to one
它是軟是一對一
it's one down
它是一個一個下
it also has two soft tides
它也有兩個軟潮
also like people
也是跟人一樣
It's the one on the left
就是左邊出一個
There is one on the right
右邊出一個這樣
in this way
這樣子
come please
來 請
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
謝謝老師精采的演講
I think one problem is
我想有一個問題就是
the same gene
同一個基因
its on that fruit fly
它在那個果蠅身上
Symptoms of its manifestation in humans
它在人類身上的表現的症狀
are different
是不一樣的
So if we want to study the genetics of a human
那如果說我們想要研究一個人類的基因
its words for some changes in human behavior
它對人類行為的一些改變的話
So if we don't see some behaviors of diseases like that in fruit flies
那如果我們在果蠅上看不到那樣子的疾病的一些行為
presented words
呈現的話
So how should we proceed with our research at this time?
那這種時候我們的研究要怎麼樣進行下去
Yes, now that you are doing research, of course you should find someone who can do it.
對 現在你做研究當然就去找那個可以做的
So I saw some traits in fruit flies
所以就在果蠅看到一些性狀啊
Some behaviors can be similar to people
一些行為是可以跟人相近的
Of course the man has something that the fruit fly doesn't have
那人當然有一些東西是在果蠅裡面沒有的
That's actually a lot of people do a lot you can't imagine
那可是其實有很多人做很多你想像不到
Someone uses fruit flies to study depression, avoidance
有人拿果蠅研究憂鬱症 致避症
That is once you can analyze its behavior
那就是一旦你可以分析它的行為的話
A lot of these things actually have similar
很多這類東西其實有類似的
So is this similar to the real thing?
那這個類似到底是不是真的一樣
Still need to do a lot of research to know
還要做很多的研究才知道
Sorry, there will be another problem like this
不好意思 那這樣子還會有一個問題就是
Then if we start from
那我們如果從
Some genes in Drosophila
果蠅身上的一些基因
and found out that their behavior is different from human genes
然後發現他們的行為表現和人類的基因是不同的
Then the research value of this gene in Drosophila
那這樣子果蠅這個基因的研究價值
For some of our human clinical medicine
對我們人類的一些臨床的醫學來說
what kind of contribution
有什麼樣的貢獻
We're all mostly focusing on that similar part now
我們現在都大部分著重在那個相似的部分
But it's interesting
不過很有意思就是
Fruit flies are different from people
果蠅就是跟人不一樣
so that different place
所以那個不一樣的地方
In fact, there are many things worth studying
其實也有很多是值得研究的
It just doesn't sound very appealing.
那只是好像講起來就不太那麼吸引人
Especially less attractive for research funding
尤其不太吸引研究經費
But this is also a difficulty in our drug development
不過這個也是我們開發藥物的一個困難
In fact, fruit flies are far away from people
其實果蠅離人
He said it was 75% similar
他說已經很相似75%
the mouse is closer
老鼠就更近了
We also use a lot of mice to test drugs
我們也用很多老鼠來測試藥物
People who are useful on mice are not necessarily useful
在老鼠上面很有用的人不一定有用
So it's still time for the final drug to be developed
所以還是最終藥物要開發的時候
still do some clinical
還是要做一些臨床
Only when the bed experiment is really useful
有床實驗真的有用才有
Are there any other questions?
還有沒有其他的問題
come over there
來那邊
wait a moment
稍微等一下
can you use the microphone
你用麥克風好嗎
You feel
你覺得
That's our research with nuts
那個是我們用果仁的研究
mainly to see
主要是看
just listen to see
就是聽下來主要是看
From DNA to infer its influence on disease
由DNA去推測它對疾病的影響
but if i today
但是如果我今天
just very simple
只是很單純的就是
from a functional point of view
用功能性的角度
For example, I study nuts
比方說我研究果仁的
The neural circuits of the brain are healed
大腦的神經回路好了
But we know for sure
但是我們就很明確就知道
Nuts have the same number of nerves as
果仁的神經的數目跟
Complexity and the Human Brain
複雜度跟人的大腦
there is a great feeling
是有很大的一段感
So if I research today
所以如果我今天研究了
It's me trying to get the nuts
就是我努力把果仁的
After the circuit coupon is created
circuit券建立好之後
what do you want to build
到底你我想建立
Functional of human neural circuit
人的neural circuit的functional
It is a functional neural circuit
就是functional的neural circuit
how big is the gap
有多大的差距
I think there must be a gap
我覺得差距一定是會有
but we think
可是我們認為
Hope from the structure of the brain of the nut
希望從果仁的腦的結構
how it works you'll learn some basic principles
它怎麼運作 你會學到一些基本原則
This principle can be applied to more complex brains
這個原則是可以適用到比較複雜的腦
like you go and get a simple computer
就像你去拿一台簡單的電腦
Its operation must have a lot to do with supercomputers or related
它的運作一定有很多是跟超級電腦還是有關的
So you can make some progress in understanding supercomputers from the simple
所以你從簡單的可以對瞭解超級電腦有一些進步
At least this is something that can be done
至少這個是可以做得到的事情
Now there are many difficulties in studying the human brain.
那現在要去研究人腦就有很多的困難
So many places have to
所以很多地方是不得已
Please tell me that I just had that UBX picture
請教教說剛剛有那個UBX圖片
Will grow wings Will grow two wings
會長出雙翼 會長出兩個翅膀
Is it possible to grow a third set of wings?
那是不是可能再長出第三堆翅膀
Then ask me how the UBX picture came from
然後再請教說那個UBX圖片是怎麼樣來的
Thanks
謝謝
That picture is actually very complicated
那個圖片其實很複雜
Those genes and their regulation
那幾個基因他們的調控
very very complicated
非常非常的複雜
So just that one picture
所以光那一個圖片
In fact, it is not a picture of a single point
其實它不是單一個點的圖片
it is several genes
它是好幾個基因
Several pictures put together
好幾個圖片湊在一起
to get that result
才會得到那樣的結果
That
那
Front
前面
yes it will be longer
是 還會長
long third
長第三個
No
沒有
Probably many people have tried to find a way to do it
大概很多人有去想辦法去做
So what I just saw was
所以剛才看的是
Second pectoral knot and third pectoral knot
第二胸結跟第三胸結
It is possible to do a conversion like this
可以做這樣的轉換
The first chest knot is very different
第一胸結就很不一樣
that so
那 所以
it must have some
它一定有某些的
This mechanism is blocked
這種機制是被擋掉了
So you can't activate it
所以你沒有辦法去把它活化起來
so far no one has found
到目前為止還沒有人找到
I'm very interested in that longevity gene
我對那個長壽基因很有興趣
That
那
you say he
你說他
When using that peptide to suppress it
用那個peptide去抑制它的時候
You said it was alive and well
你說它活得好好的
My impression is that it is like in that place called Xian Chong
我的印象是像在那個叫做現蟲
C.L.N.E.L.E.R. People Go for This Longevity Gene
C.L.N.E.L.E.R.人去找這種長壽基因
It turns out that it seems
結果發現好像說
those who do not eat well
那些吃得不太好的
Those who are thinner live longer
長得瘦瘦的活得比較久
But you said your vagina
可是你說你的腸陰
Don't talk about gut
不應該講腸陰
seems to be very healthy
好像說很健康
Has anyone tried to find small molecule drugs?
那有人嘗試去找小分子的藥物嗎
Then I will live longer if I eat one a day
那我一天吃一顆會比較長壽
Well
呃
In the article just now, it used peptide
剛才那一篇它是用peptide
that's been years
那已經好幾年了
So I guess someone used
所以我猜想是有人用
go find little medicine
去找小藥物
that small molecule
那小分子
uh haven't seen anything yet
呃 還沒有看到什麼
not yet
目前還沒有
All right
好吧
hurry up or i
要快一點 不然我
Ha ha ha ha
哈哈哈哈
no
不是
Are there any other questions?
還有沒有其他的問題
good if
好 如果
if not we then
如果沒有的話我們再
Thank you next time Professor Sun
下次謝謝孫教授